本字幕由人人影视字幕组翻译
禁止用作任何商业盈利行为
本字幕由人人影视电影组与纪录片组联合译制
他从四楼坠落
It was a four-story fall...
从屋顶摔落在水泥路面上
From the top of the roof to the concrete pavement below.
他刚过完29岁生日
He had just passed his 29th birthday.
这里是911  请问需要什么帮助
911. Can I help you?
-我需要急救人员  -有人坠楼了
- I need a paramedic. He fell.
从多高的地方摔下去的
How far did he fall?
从四楼摔下去的  大概有12米高
He fell four stories, which would be 40 feet.
嘴里有血  除此之外
Blood in his mouth, and other than that,
不清楚是否有别处受伤
I don't know if there's any other injuries.
我们一整天都在互发短信
We had been texting each other all day.
我们去楼顶拍几张照片
千万不要靠近边缘啊  我说真的
哈哈  我不会的
他叫汤姆
His name was Tom.
他曾是我的生命
And he was my life.
自我们交往初期
At the beginning of our relationship,
我和汤姆就有很多相似之处
Tom and I bonded over the many similarities we had.
谢恩的视频日记 2011年5月
我们都从小听乡村音乐长大
We both grew up listening to country music.
加斯·布鲁克斯同是我们最喜欢的乡村歌手
Garth Brooks is our favorite country artist.
冥冥之中  我们都认为《曼舞》
And, somehow, we both agreed that "The Dance"
是我们最爱的乡村歌曲
is our favorite country song.
如果说有人
If there was ever a person
能够完美诠释其歌词  那非汤姆莫属
to truly emulate the lyrics of this song, it was Tom.
♪拥着你
♪Holding you
拥着你
Holding you...
♪我便拥有了一切
♪I held everything
我便拥有了一切
I held everything.
♪那一刻
♪For a moment
那一刻
For a moment...
♪我已于世界之巅
♪Wasn't I the king?
我已于世界之巅
Wasn't I the king?
♪未曾想
♪But if I'd only known
♪我亦会陨落
♪How the king would fall
♪谁说得准
♪Hey, who's to say
♪我能避免这一切
♪You know, I might have changed it all
♪而如今
♪And now
♪我庆幸当时不知
♪I'm glad I didn't know
♪会这样收尾
♪The way it all would end
♪会这样飘散
♪The way it all would go
♪我们的生命
♪Our lives
♪最好交给命运
♪Are better left to chance
♪我本可避免伤痛
♪I could have missed the pain
♪但亦会错失
♪But I'd have had to miss
♪这支曼舞
♪The dance
新郎
同性恋孩子想在蒙大拿卡利斯佩尔镇
Kalispell, Montana, is probably not the easiest place
长大很不容易
to have a child grow up who is gay.
我们那里的人
Our community is --
辛迪   \fn方正兰亭黑_GBK\fs20谢恩的母亲
不能说是不开窍
You don't want to say backwoodsy,
但是  他们生活在闭塞的乡村
But, you know, they're rural,
因此无法接受与他们不同的人
and so they don't accept people who are different.
谢恩出生那天
The day Shane was born,
我被迫离开医院
I had to get a special leave from the hospital
去签署离婚协议
to go sign my divorce papers.
我因此成了医院里人尽皆知的八卦
So I was the talk of the hospital
因为我们镇非常小
'cause we're a small, little town,
那算是我生命中非常特殊的时刻
and that was kind of a special moment in my life.
我觉得
I think that, you know,
他们结婚可能过于草率
they might have gotten married too soon, possibly,
所以慢慢得就分开了
and they kind of just grew apart.
我爸爸  他个性很强
My dad, he's a character.
他在大学里是摔跤选手  还喜欢打猎
He was a wrestler in college, and he loves hunting.
他打猎我本来一直跟着
I would go hunting with my dad,
但突然间
and all of a sudden,
他每打中一头鹿  我都会嚎啕大哭
after he'd shoot a deer, I would end up in tears,
因为我脑子里一直在想小鹿斑比
'cause I kept thinking "Bambi" --
想着  "我爸爸打死了小鹿斑比"
Like, "My dad just shot Bambi."
一段时间之后  他就再也不带我去打猎了
After a while, he stopped taking me hunting.
我跟爸爸说好  等我长大之后
I made a deal with my dad, growing up,
我会尝试各种不同的运动
that I would try all different sports.
他打过棒球
He tried baseball.
打过篮球
He tried basketball.
全都打过
He tried them all.
我记得有一次他们输了
I remember one loss they had,
戴维   \fn方正兰亭黑_GBK\fs20谢恩的父亲
谢恩根本没怎么上场  可他难过极了
and Shane hardly played at all, but, boy, he took it hard.
真的特别可爱
And that was pretty cute,
但他算不上优秀的球员
but he wasn't much of a contributor.
我对谢恩的第一印象是在学校舞台剧上
My first memory of Shane was at a school play,
塔米   \fn方正兰亭黑_GBK\fs20邻家母亲
他在台上唱歌跳舞
and he was just singing, dancing --
使出浑身解数来逗大家开心
whatever he could do to entertain, he was doing it.
我们用红色亮片做了一辆车
We had made a car. We used red glitter.
谢恩的眼中就只有那辆车
And Shane wanted that car like none other.
他四年级的时候
He was in fourth grade,
我记得他跟老师说
and I remember him telling his teacher
他高中毕业后
that, when he graduated from high school,
要去加利福尼亚
he was going to California.
我就想  "为什么"
And I just thought, "Why is that?"
那真的很奇怪
You know, that just seemed so strange.
米凯拉   \fn方正兰亭黑_GBK\fs20谢恩的发小
他唱芭芭拉·史翠珊歌的样子我仍记忆犹新
I particularly remember him singing Barbra Streisand.
他在屋里不停绕着圈跑
He was running around the room in circles
当着每个人的面唱
and singing right in everyone's face --
米凯拉   \fn方正兰亭黑_GBK\fs20谢恩的发小
♪你没有送花给我
♪ You don't bring me flowers
非常迷人  特别无畏
Like, just so charismatic and so unafraid.
我上小学的时候
I was in elementary school,
有时候会做那样的事
and what I would do sometimes is --
我不想上床睡觉
I didn't want to go to bed,
而妈妈让我去睡觉
and my mom would tell me to go to bed,
然后我就偷偷溜下床
and then I would sneak out
坐在她的躺椅后面看电视
and sit behind her recliner and watch the TV,
因为我想叛逆一下
'cause I wanted to kind of be a little rebel.
有一次  她在看《费城故事》
One time, she was watching the movie "Philadelphia."
等到电影结束的时候
Finally, it got to the end of the movie,
我知道那个男的是同性恋
and I knew that this guy was gay,
我知道他病了
and I knew that he was sick
而且因为同性恋的身份  他就快死了
and he was dying because of being gay,
那深深地引起了我的共鸣
and that really -- it struck a chord with me
因为我意识到  我就和他一样
'cause I knew that...I was like him.
他喜欢上了另一个男人  结果瞧瞧发生了什么
That guy liked another guy, and look what happened --
他越来越消瘦  越来越虚弱
he kept getting thinner, he kept getting pale,
他的脸上  身上都长满了脓疮
And there was like sores on his face and his body,
我记得当时在想  "这就是我今后的模样"
and I just remember thinking that, "That's gonna be me.
"我也会变成这样"
That's gonna happen to me."
他变得比以前安静了
He got quieter,
也没那么有趣了
and he wasn't as fun to be around.
你能看得出他有心事
You could tell that something was always on his mind,
莉兹   \fn方正兰亭黑_GBK\fs20谢恩的姐姐
有些事一直在困扰着他
Something was always bothering him,
但你就是不知道是什么
but you never knew what it was.
一天晚上  我记得谢恩走进我的房间
One night, I remember Shane coming into my room,
他说  "妈  我要死于艾滋病了"
and he said, "Mom, I'm dying of A.I.D.S."
我问  "亲爱的  为什么这么说"
And I said, "Honey, why are you saying that?"
他说  "因为电影是这么演的"
and he goes, "Well, because of that movie."
我告诉他  "亲爱的  你没有艾滋病"
And I said, "Well, honey, you don't have A.I.D.S."
那时我才真正注意到
And that's when I really noticed
谢恩得了焦虑症
Shane starting to have panic attacks.
帕特 谢恩的曾祖母                        朱迪  \fn方正兰亭黑_GBK\fs20谢恩的祖母
他感觉无法呼吸
He felt like he couldn't breathe.
我们不得不跟他说
And we would have to say,
"你得往头上套个袋子"
"You've got to put a sack over your head."
吸入二氧化碳可以平衡恐慌发作时体内酸碱度  防止过度呼吸导致的呼吸性碱中毒
他不喜欢那样做
He didn't like doing it,
但如果是在我家  我们就会给他套个袋子
but when he was at my house, we put a sack over his head.
随着时间推移
So as time went on,
我会偷偷溜进家里的某间卧室
I would sneak into one of the bedrooms in our house
然后拨911  说我快死了
and I would dial 911 and tell them that I was dying.
突然间
And all of a sudden,
我看见车道上有很多灯在闪
I see these flashing lights in the driveway,
我就想  "出什么事了"
and I thought, "What is going on?"
我上楼之后  急救人员说
And I go upstairs, and here is the ambulance
家里有人遇到麻烦了
saying that somebody is in distress in this home.
有人噎住了  有人窒息了
Somebody was choking. Somebody was suffocating.
她就会说  "谢恩  该死的"
It led to her being like, you know, "Shane, god damn it!
"警察怎么又来了"
The cops are here again."
从他六年级开始一直到高中
From sixth grade, till I got that kid through high school,
我都不知道自己是怎么撑下来的
I didn't know if I was gonna survive.
我敢说他报了10到15次警
I bet 10, 15 times he called 911.
我花的钱
The money
那么多年来我在那上面花的钱
That it, you know, cost me through the years --
可以说是压力不小
It was very stressful.
但他的确很痛苦  我知道他很痛苦
But it was real to him, and I knew it was real to him,
我想要他有安全感
And I wanted him to feel he was safe.
她最终发现
She finally decided
状况已经严重到超出她能掌控的地步了
that this is maybe more serious than she can handle,
所以她带我去看了心理医生
so she set me up with a therapist.
等谢恩完成他的疗程之后
When Shane got done with his session,
医生把我叫进去  对我说
he asked me to come in, and he said,
"你儿子需要接受他是同性恋这个事实"
"Your son just needs to admit to himself that he's gay,
"一切都会好起来的"
and everything will be fine."
我说  "你怎么能这样说呢"
And I said, "How can you say that?
"他不是同性恋"
He's not gay."
豪瑟医生说  "那好吧"
And Doctor Hausser said, "Well, you know,
"看来你也需要坦然接受这个事实"
That's something you're gonna have to come to peace with."
我一直很怀疑  不骗你
I always suspected -- I'm not gonna lie to you.
我花了几天时间接受这个事实
It took me a couple days to process,
然后我就决定
and the thing it come down to is,
"我不会再要其他孩子了"
"I ain't making any more kids --
"我还是跟这几个孩子好好过吧"
I better stay in good with the ones I got."
我无条件地爱他  所以这并不重要
And I love him unconditionally, so it just doesn't matter.
有趣的是  当我还是个小孩子
It's kind of funny now that, here I was a little boy,
我跪在地上  向上帝祈祷自己不是同性恋
on my knees, praying to God that I wouldn't be gay,
与此同时有另外一个男孩
and there was another little boy
在2400公里以外的印第安纳做着同样的事
1,500 miles away in Indiana doing the same thing.
同性恋孩子想在印第安纳诺克斯市
Knox, Indiana, is not the easiest place
长大很不容易
for a gay kid to grow up.
那里文化很单一  不够多元
It's very homogenous -- not much diversity there.
马克   \fn方正兰亭黑_GBK\fs20汤姆的发小
我认识汤姆
I knew Tom
是因为我俩的哥哥都曾当过童子军
when both of our brothers were in boy scouts together.
大家都喜欢他
Everybody loved him.
他就是那种人见人爱的孩子
And he was just the popular kid.
非常有同情心
He had a lot of empathy.
我永远不会忘记  我母亲去世那天
I'll never forget, the day my mom died,
汤姆是第一个来我家的人
Tom was the first person to come over to my house.
他走进大门  哭哭啼啼的
He walked in the door, and he was crying --
好像他比我还伤心
You know, almost like he's sadder than I am.
汤姆的父母在之前的婚姻中
Tom's mother and father each had children
都有各自的孩子
from previous marriages.
汤姆则是他俩唯一共同生下的孩子
So, Tom was the only child between the two parents,
是全家人的掌上明珠
and he was the center of attention in the family.
他到哪都是焦点人物
He was the center of attention everywhere he was.
汤姆经常在家里弹琴
Tom would always be playing the piano at home,
唱歌  跳舞
singing, dancing around.
♪来吧  宝贝
♪ Come on, baby
♪你让我癫狂
♪ You're driving me crazy
♪我的老天
♪ Goodness gracious
♪好一团热情的火焰
♪ Great balls of fire!
他在蹦床上耍各种杂技
He was doing his tricks on the trampoline,
总是在表现自己
and he was always performing.
对汤姆来说  怎么表现都不为过
For Tom, there was never any such thing as too much.
汤姆的父亲  只是个普通蓝领工人
Tom's dad, he was a simple blue-collar worker,
早出晚归
came home late, got up really early the next day,
日复一日
and, you know, did it again.
他父母为了汤姆的幸福牺牲了很多
Both of his parents sacrificed a lot for Tom's happiness.
为了让汤姆进柯尔沃
His mom took a job as a janitor
他母亲找了份清洁工的工作
so that Tom could go to Culver.
柯尔沃  美国一流高中
没有多少父母会这么做
Not many parents would do that --
为了让孩子接受最好的教育
would start cleaning toilets so their son could have
而跑去洗厕所
the best education.
汤姆的父亲曾在越南服役
Tom's dad was in Vietnam, and that's why
因此他高中时去了趟越南
he went to Vietnam when he was in high school.
他十分钦佩父亲为国奋战的行为
He definitely respected his dad for fighting for his country.
我觉得  随着汤姆不断长大
I think, as Tom got older,
随着他逐渐萌生自己的想法
as Tom became his own person,
他俩也变得愈发难以沟通
it just became difficult for them to connect.
汤姆总是固执地
Tom was always very adamant
说着自己的想法
about saying what he believed in,
而他父亲则无法接受
and it didn't work with his dad.
真是悲哀  但我真的认为
And it's sad, but I really think that,
谢恩的视频日记 高中二年级
如果更多人愿意给我机会跟他们做朋友
if more people would give me a chance to be their friend,
我可以证明给他们看
I could show them that,
即使我和他们不完全一样
it's just 'cause I'm not exactly like them,
但我依然是个好人
but I'm still a good person.
工作人员:
欢迎来到冰雪皇后                                     可以为您点餐
最近怎么样
Hi. How's it going?
你少来  谢恩
怎么
What?
我就是来买和平常一样的
I'm just coming to get the usual.
好吧  请放6.74刀在窗口
好的  谢谢
All right. Thank you.
真是悲哀
It's kind of pathetic
他们每次都知道我要什么
if they know exactly what I get every time.
在卡利斯佩尔
In Kalispell, seriously,
吃冰雪皇后的成千上万
there's tons of people at Dairy Queen.
这里很不错
It's the cool place to be.
让我看看
Yeah, let's see.
怎么
What?
她把镜头挡住了
She just closed the camera.
在那  在那
Oh, there's -- there's --
天啊  他们把窗户挡上了
Oh, geez. They closed the windows.
我其实在这上班
I actually worked here,
但我不想告诉别人我在这上班
but I didn't tell people that I worked here.
我得承认
I have to admit
我想成为那种人
that I want to be one of those people
那种人们见到就会说
that people are like, "Ooh!
"哇  他真帅"
Whoa! He looks good."
我喜欢跑步
'Cause I enjoy running,
但我只在自己家的跑步机上跑
but when I run, it's on a treadmill in our house,
因为我不想让人看到我跑步的样子
because I do not want people seeing me running.
我完全不想让别人看到我
I do not want people to see me, really, at all.
有件事我一直很渴望
The one thing that I wanted
就是有一个愿意和我聊天交朋友
was just someone that I could talk to and relate to,
并接受真实自我的人
that accepted me for being me.
我曾迷恋上了一个叫马特·帕克的男孩
I developed a crush for a guy named Matt Parker.
我们可以整晚待在彼此的家里
And we would spend the night at each other's houses all the time.
我们一起出门打篮球
We would play basketball outside.
是最好的朋友
We were just best friends.
到了高中  我终于鼓起勇气
It was in high school that I finally got the courage
告诉马特我的感受  我给他写了封情书
to tell Matt how I felt, and I wrote him a love letter.
我很紧张
I was nervous.
写情书这事我真的很紧张
I was so nervous about giving him the letter.
但他告诉我他不是同性恋
But he had to tell me that he's not gay.
我很伤心  但同时
And it broke my heart, but at the same time,
我也很高兴  因为他愿意继续做我朋友
I was still so happy that he was willing to be my friend.
当时高中里有这么几个人
There was a situation with a couple friends in high school,
他们质疑他的性向
and they were questioning his sexuality
斯科特   \fn方正兰亭黑_GBK\fs20谢恩的高中朋友
并且...  嘲笑他
and kind of were, you know, mocking him,
拿他开玩笑
making fun of him,
他的几个朋友也对他避之不及
And a couple of his friends completely shunning him.
我接到他好朋友母亲的电话
I got a phone call from one of his best friend's mother,
她想让我过去一趟
and she wanted me to come over.
她很生气
She was very upset.
当我妈告诉我她要去马特家时
Once my mom told me that she was going over to Matt's house,
我立刻预感到这不会是好事
I knew immediately this was not gonna be good.
那也算不上一封真正意义上的情书
It wasn't, you know, really a love, love letter.
只是写了他很欣赏马特
It was just, you know, he admired Matt,
喜欢和他在一起的时光
he enjoyed his time,
在我看来更像是一封宣誓友谊的信
and it was just, I thought, like a good friendship letter.
没有让人反感的文字
It was nothing distasteful.
和性无关
It was nothing sexual.
只是说了他对他的感觉
It was just telling him how he felt about him.
我让她说完了她想说的话
I let her say everything she wanted to say,
然后我告诉她
and after she was done, I just told her,
我说  "你不用再担心了"
I said, "You'll never have to worry about this again,
"因为谢恩不会再和马特一起玩了"
because Shane will never be around Matt,
"我也不想再跟你有什么联系"
and I don't want to ever hear from you again."
我不想复述我对她说的原话
I don't want to say what I really told her.
那不太礼貌  我大概是告诉她
It wasn't polite, and I just told her, basically,
离我们远点  别骚扰我儿子
take the flying leap and to leave my son alone.
马特的父母在社区里很有地位
Matt's parents were very prominent in the community.
他父亲是校长
His dad was a principal.
他母亲是教师
His mom was a teacher.
校长告诉我
I was told by the principal
我不得参加
that I wasn't allowed
任何体育比赛
to go to any sporting events,
因为马特在队里
Because Matt was on the teams.
那是块大场地
That was the big place to be.
镇上所有的人都会去
That was where everyone in town was,
而谢恩却被禁止出席
and Shane wasn't welcome.
马特也在同一个教区
Matt was also in the same church community,
谢恩也因此无法
and Shane wasn't able
跟小伙伴们一起参加一次重要的旅行
to go on a very important trip with his youth group.
因为马特的父母不允许他去
Matt's parents made it so he couldn't go,
他为那次旅行攒了许多钱
and he had raised all this money to go on this trip,
他很绝望
and he was devastated.
他表现出无所谓的样子
He acted like it was no big deal,
但能看出来他很受打击
but you could tell he was hurt.
情书发出去之后
Once this letter came out,
这个男孩和他家长闹得满城风雨
this boy and his parents went and shouted it to the world.
学校里的孩子不断找他麻烦
Kids at school were constantly picking on him.
他不再被大家接受
He wasn't accepted anymore.
他们叫他基佬
They called him gay.
叫他娘泡
They called him fag.
他们给他起得名字都难听极了
The names that they called him were just horrendous.
雅各布 谢恩最喜欢的老师
有一种心态被称为"牛仔精神"
There's a mentality of the "Cowboy way"
而那对同性恋并不认可
which does not include people that are gay.
因此在那里生活很难
So it's a tough place.
在他被禁止参加这些活动前
Before he was banned,
谢恩参加过一次橄榄球比赛
Shane was at a football game,
所有孩子都在奖杯里吐口水
and all these kids started spitting in this cup.
然后据我所知
And next thing I know, the one kid
一位曾经是谢恩非常要好的朋友拿着奖杯
that used to be a real good friend of shane's had this cup,
想将其倒扣在谢恩的头上
and he was just about ready to tip it on Shane's head.
我跟你说  要说起
And let me tell you -- if you want to talk
母熊护子
about a mother bear protecting her cub,
我当时都气疯了
this woman came unglued.
我说  "把那该死的奖杯放下  离他远点"
I said, "You put that damn cup down, and leave him alone."
看着这种事发生在我儿子身上太让人心疼了
It was just heartbreaking to see that happen to my son.
谢恩的视频日记 高中三年级
在与马特和他家人的种种闹剧结束后
It was after all the drama with Matt and his family
我的心情十分阴暗
that I just went to a really dark place,
我崩溃了
and I had a breakdown.
我接到了学校的电话通知
I got a call from the school informing me
说我儿子已经两周没去学校了
my son hasn't been to school for two weeks.
其他孩子让他生不如死
Other kids made his life literally a living hell,
而且毫无好转迹象
and it never really got better,
我认为他也看不到希望
And I don't think he ever saw it would get better,
所以他直接不去上学了
and that's why he just stopped going.
一天晚上  我和三个女儿
One evening, all three daughters and I
一起去家具城
went to the furniture store,
那天是他的生日
and it was his birthday,
他只是孤零零地跟妈妈逛街
And he was by himself, just hanging out with his mom.
他的情绪很低落
He was very depressed.
他不再是以前那个谢恩了
He was not shane.
好像变成了一具空壳
He was like a shell of himself.
我为自己给家人带来的难堪与伤害
I was sick of the embarrassment and the pain
谢恩的姐妹
感到深深的痛苦
that I was bringing to my family.
我觉得唯一能让他们解脱的办法
I felt like the only way that I can make their lives better
就是独自一人去面对
is by taking my own.
那天在爸爸的住处  只有我一个人在家
I was at my dad's house, I was home alone,
我走到他放枪的地方
And I just walked over to his gun case.
取出了一把枪
And I took one of the guns,
之后回到了客厅
And I just went back in the living room,
我拿着枪  坐在那儿
And I just sat there, and I held it.
想了很多很多
I mean, there was so many thoughts,
那时  我脑子里一片混乱
like, going through my head at that moment.
我苦苦挣扎了一个多小时
It was like for over an hour, just really contemplating,
做着艰难的抉择
like, what my next step should be.
还好  我意识到了
Fortunately, I also thought through
选择死亡对我的亲人太不公平
in that it wouldn't be fair to my family.
对我妈妈也不公平
It wouldn't be fair to my mom.
我不得不考虑
And I just had to visualize
如果我就这样结束了自己的生命
what the experience would be like for them
我的家人会遭受怎样的痛苦
if I did take my life.
这不值得
And it wouldn't be worth it.
同样在某程度上  我相信
Also, on some level, I must have believed
总会有那么一天
that, somehow, someday,
会出现这么一个人
there's gonna be someone out there
他会很单纯地爱上我这个人
who's gonna love me for me.
汤姆就是有这样的气质
Tom just had this presence.
充满活力
He had this energy.
他总是不停地唱啊跳啊
He was always singing and laughing
享受生活
and enjoying life so much.
♪军功卓著的将军有颗金子般的心
♪ There was a decorated general with a heart of gold
演唱: 汤姆
他是班里的佼佼者
He was at the top of his class.
无论是体育运动  还是学校功课
He was a leader in all aspects of the word,
他总是门门全优
in sports, and in school.
♪在战场上
♪ On the battlefield...
阿曼达
汤姆在柯尔沃军事学院的好友
你每次见到汤姆的时候
Every time you met Tom,
就像见到了自己最好的朋友一样
it felt like you were meeting your best friend.
不管你是谁
And it didn't matter who you were --
他总是无条件支持你
He always had your back.
我认为汤姆没有去本地的高中
I think Tom went to Culver
而是选择了柯尔沃
instead of the high school in his hometown,
是因为他觉得这是个
because he saw it as an opportunity
开阔眼界的机会
to open his horizons,
为此  他的父母功不可没
And, you know, his parents played a big role in that.
他妈妈在柯尔沃工作
His mom worked at culver,
因此他们才能支付减免的学费
primarily so that they could afford the reduced tuition,
因此汤姆才有了以后那些机会
so that Tom would have all those opportunities.
高三那年  他向我吐露心声
He came out to me our senior year.
那天晚上  我们坐在草地上
It was at night, and we were sitting in the grass,
我只记得  他突然变得很严肃
and I remember he got really serious all of a sudden,
他说  "我有事要告诉你"
And he said, "I have something to tell you --
"我是同性恋"
I'm gay."
之后他就把头埋了下去
Then he put his head in his lap,
哭了出来  他的情绪很激动
And he was crying and really emotional about it.
我想他真的很害怕被人说三道四
I think he was really afraid of being judged.
可我并没有感到惊讶
It didn't surprise me at all.
因为这位男性朋友
This is coming from my friend who,
在三四个星期之前
probably three or four weeks ago,
刚在他家后院里玩蹦床的时候
was singing "I'm a barbie girl,"
高歌过一曲《芭比娃娃》
while jumping on a trampoline in his backyard.
水叮当乐团风靡全球的卡通舞曲
瓦萨学院
他认识所有人  大家也都知道他
He knew everybody, and everybody knew him.
因为总和他在一起
I felt like my popularity scale rose
我觉得自己也变得出名了
just because I hung out with him.
上学的时候  汤姆和安妮·海瑟薇是朋友
Tom was friends with Anne Hathaway in school.
还有汤姆·汉克斯的女儿
He also was friends with Tom Hanks' daughter.
萨沙 汤姆在瓦萨学院的好友
我总是不停地在想
I never could wrap my mind around it,
这就是汤姆  这个洋溢着中西部风情
because here was tom, this sort of midwestern,
啃着玉米和美国派长大的壮小伙
Corn-fed, american-pie-eating guy,
来自印第安纳州的一个小镇
who came from this tiny town in Indiana,
他上过军校
who then went to military school.
他总是能在社交
He was able to get along and succeed
和学业之间游刃有余
in that entire social circle and academic circle.
后来他来到了自由的瓦萨学院
And then went to Vassar, which is this liberal place
那里的氛围完全不同
and a completely different vibe.
他的经历简直令人难以置信
He just sort of was magic.
汤姆  他那么英俊
Tom, for as beautiful as he was and, you know
爱丽克丝 汤姆在瓦萨学院的好友
这一点  他自己也清楚
the fact that he knew how beautiful he was,
可他从不关注别人的长相
He did not care at all about how other people looked.
他不在乎你是从哪里来的
And he did not care where you came from,
你开什么样的车
what car you drove.
他只是很单纯地接纳你这个人
He just accepted anybody and everybody for who they were,
可能是由于他的同志身份
and I think because he was gay,
他了解那些逆主流
and because he knew what it was like
不被大众接受的感受
to be not the mainstream, normal person.
他对我说过很多次
He told me many times
因为我有听力障碍而对我十分钦佩
how much he respected me because I was hearing-impaired.
与其他20出头的年轻人不同  他经常对我说
What 20-something-year-old says to you,
"天哪  太不可思议了  你怎么做到的"
"Wow, you're amazing -- you've done so much"?
"我真是太崇拜你了"
"I'm in total awe of you --"
谁会这样说呢  没人这样说
Who says that? Nobody.
他会吟唱古典音乐
He gave recitals of classical music.
他写出的歌词感人肺腑
He wrote incredibly heartfelt lyrics.
但他同时也是个硬汉  可以把你打得落花流水
But he was tough, 'cause he could kick your ass.
能够把你摔倒在地
He could wrestle you down.
我知道他爸爸很严厉
I know that his dad was very stern.
在一定程度上  他认为
The idea of manhood and masculinity
男子汉一定要有阳刚之气
and presenting yourself in a certain way
这一点对他来说很重要
was important to him.
他希望汤姆也能够成为那样的男子汉
I think he wanted to have Tom basically play that role.
在这一点上  汤姆做得很好
And Tom knew how to play it very well.
我和汤姆之间
There was definitely
有一个从没说出口的共识
an unspoken understanding between Tom and I
那就是他的同志身份
that he was gay.
我知道他一直在为此挣扎
And I know that was a struggle for him,
因为他始终没有告诉自己的父母
because he still hadn't told his parents.
我想汤姆一定是担心
I think Tom was literally worried
他爸爸知道后会宰了他吧
that his dad would kill him.
我正在离开卡利斯佩尔的路上
Well, I'm leaving Kalispell right now,
谢恩的视频日记 2004年8月
现在大概3点左右
And it's roughly 3:00.
没错  我很紧张
And, yep, I am nervous.
我和家里人说的时候
I have been talking to my family,
他们都在不停地哭
And everyone's crying and doing that whole thing.
我现在拿出手机假装打电话
I'm gonna be on my cellphone
这样看起来不会像在自言自语
So it looks like I'm not talking to myself.
他们给我钱  让我注意安全
Everyone gave me money and told me to be safe.
我现在出发了
So, here I go.
毕业之后  他拿到了
After graduation, he got a scholarship
镇上一所学校的奖学金
to go to the school here in town.
我很不情愿他放弃这个机会
and so it was hard for me to not have him take it.
可他想去加利福尼亚
'cause he wanted to go to California.
我知道  他去了好莱坞之后
I knew, when he went to Hollywood,
一切都会好起来的
he was going to be okay,
在那里  他会遇到许多和他一样的同性恋者
and he can mix in with where a lot of gay people were.
我甚至不知道他走了
I didn't even know he went to --
我的脑子不好使了
my mind is gone.
记性不太好
I can't remember many things.
谢恩的视频日记 2004年8月
加利福尼亚州
我们第一次见到谢恩
We first met Shane
是在蒙大拿州米苏拉的一次家族婚礼上
At a family wedding in Missoula, Montana.
他说  "最后  我还是决定去加州"
He said, "Eventually, I'd like to move to california."
保罗和马克 谢恩的雇主及朋友
三个月之后
Well, three months later,
我们接到他的电话  说他到了
We got a phone call from him that he was here.
我们竭尽所能地帮助他
So we kind of tried to steer him --
帮他找工作  安排住处
Helping him get a job, a place to live.
我们就像成了他的养父母
And we became like his adopted parents.
我想他当时刚满18岁
I think he was barely 18 years old,
里克 谢恩的房东
还是个瘦弱的卷毛小子
This thin kid with curly hair,
刚从蒙大纳州来到了大城市
out of Montana into the big city.
他很安静  很保守
He was very quiet, very reserved.
珍妮和婕尔萨 谢恩的良师益友
他给我看了几张自拍照
He showed me some head shots that he took.
他的头发很卷  长得像李伯拉斯
He had wavy, wavy hair, and he looked like Liberace.
李伯拉斯  美国著名同性恋钢琴家
没错  没错  没错
Oh. Right. Right, right.
-我就想  "天呐"  -没错
- And I thought, "Oh, my god." - Right.
"我该和这孩子说些什么呢"
"What am I gonna tell this kid?"
珍妮和婕尔萨 谢恩的良师益友
谢恩说他想当演员
Shane said he wanted to be an actor.
可没过多久  我们就明白了
But after a very short time, it became clear
他只是想来加利福尼亚而已
he just wanted to get to California.
我找到了一份工作
I got a job
给一部电视剧做制片助理
working as a production assistant for a TV show.
谢恩和我是在录像带库里认识的
Shane and I met in the tape vault,
可以算得上是一见钟情
and it was pretty much love at first sight.
切尔西 好友
他有种小镇男孩的特质
He's got that small-town kind of quality to him.
讨人喜欢  搞笑  同时为人谦逊
He's just so likeable and funny and so humble.
切尔西 好友
谢恩对事对人有着与众不同的看法
Shane doesn't necessarily see sort of what everyone else sees.
一位与我共事的好友
One of my friends that I worked with,
邀请我去和她的一个朋友打保龄球
she invited me to go bowling with one of her friends.
我们有个想法
We had this idea
让汤姆和谢恩相互认识一下
that we had to get Tom and Shane to meet each other.
丽兹 好友
不过没告诉他们这是我们刻意安排的
But we didn't tell them that it was a setup.
她跟我说有个叫汤姆的人也会去
She said that there was gonna be this guy there named Tom
他在这个行业中十分活跃
and that he's active in the industry,
《新闻周刊》平面模特照
所以她觉得结识他  会对我今后的发展有帮助
So she thought that maybe it would be a good person to be connected with.
我们到了那里
We get there.
他非常引人注目
He is ridiculously attractive --
可以说帅气逼人  魅力非凡
gorgeous, if you will -- so charismatic.
他当过演员
He was an actor.
拍过几部戏
I think he had been in a few things.
就在此时
And almost immediately,
谢恩开始怀疑我们的目的
Shane became skeptical.
我们喜欢这些男人
性感的邻家男孩
他开始问"这家伙是谁"
He was like, "who is this guy?"
我反问他"他为何让你如此纠结  谢恩"
And I'm like, "why is he bothering you so much, Shane?"
他比我大四岁
He was four years older than me.
去过很多地方
Like, he had traveled the world,
会说外语
you know, spoke a different language.
会演奏好几种乐器
He played a bunch of instruments.
他总是自信满满的样子
He was just so cocky and confident,
当然  保龄球也打得很好
and, well, of course, he, like, was bowling really well.
而我  连五个瓶都击不倒
And then here I am, like, can't even knock five pins down.
在打完保龄球不久之后
So, it wasn't too long after we went bowling
我们又在我朋友莉兹的公寓里碰到了
that we all got together again at my friend Lizzy's apartment.
就在那天晚上
It was that night
我们终于互换了手机号码
that we finally exchanged phone numbers.
我们一起出去玩
We ended up hanging out,
四处周游
you know, a few times here and there.
他一直唱歌  总是很开心的样子
And he was always singing. He was always happy.
♪生活就像高速公路
♪ Life is a highway
♪我要星夜兼程
♪ I want to ride it all night long
我和汤姆  我们白天一直待在一起
Tom and I, we would spend all day together,
之后他回自己家
and then he would go home,
然后  晚上的时候
which would lead to, later in the evening,
我们还要讲上几个小时的电话
talking on the phone for a few hours.
没过多久
It did not take long
我就觉得与汤姆相处很愉快
for me to really feel comfortable with Tom,
可以对他无所不谈
that I could tell him anything.
可以信任他一辈子
Like, I trusted him with my life.
汤姆是个很自信的人
Tom was a very confident person.
是他主动追求谢恩
He went after Shane.
起初  谢恩的反应是"天呐"
At first, Shane was like, "aah,"
因为他从没谈过恋爱
'cause he had never been in a relationship before.
这对他来说是初恋
This was his, you know, first love.
我们有次去听汤姆演唱
We went to hear Tom one time,
谢恩会在他表演的时候环顾四周
and Shane would look around the room while he was playing
因为他想让所有人都专心听他唱歌
because he wanted to make sure everybody was paying attention
并对他同样狂热
and seeing what he saw.
有一个犹太单词叫做自豪
And there is a Jewish word called kvell.
那正是汤姆表演时他脸上的神情
And that's what he looked like when Tom performed --
他无比自豪
he was kvelling.
热情洋溢
He was glowing.
终于体验到爱情的滋味非常美妙
It was incredible to finally experience that feeling of love,
有如心花怒放一般
you know, like the butterflies.
这正是我想象中我的朋友们有过的感受
It's what I always imagined that all my friends felt.
没过多久  我就搬进了他的公寓
It didn't take long for me to move into his apartment.
他们很快就走到了一起
They got very close very quickly.
我认为他们能走到一起并不是因为搬去了洛杉矶
I think their freedom wasn't moving to L.A.
而是由于汤姆为谢恩创造了
I think Tom was definitely the door for Shane
认同自己的机会
to come to terms with himself.
汤姆是他的避风港
Tom was a safe place.
汤姆认识谢恩的时候  他就像只迷失的羊
When Tom met Shane, he was a little, lost sheep.
汤姆真的把谢恩照顾的很好
And Tom really looked out for Shane.
他喜欢给我做饭  哪怕他累了一天
He loved making dinner even when he was really tired.
他喜欢替我系领带
He loved tying my ties --
甚至用专门的方法帮我叠衬衫
even properly tucking my shirt in,
因为柯尔沃教过他该怎么弄
because at Culver, they teach you how to do all that.
汤姆一心追求他的梦想
Tom truly was pursuing his dreams,
而谢恩明白账单需要有人支付
and Shane knew that bills had to be paid.
谢恩是个很理性地人
Shane was the level-headed one.
一人没考虑周全的地方  另一人可以互补
What one couldn't think of, the other one could.
他们发现彼此之间有很多共同点
They found an awful lot in common.
他们都是浪漫主义者
They were both romantics.
他们都来自小镇
They're both from small towns.
都希望让世人对他们刮目相看
Both wanted to make an impression on the world.
艾莉森 汤姆的好友
他们总是面带微笑  生活得很开心
They were always smiling and always having a good time.
他们是那种让你相信爱情的情侣
I mean, they're the kind of couple that makes you believe in love.
艾琳 好友
我喜欢看他们斗嘴
I just loved their bickering,
那简直是打情骂俏
which was really flirting.
在他们感情中  我最喜欢那个部分
That was probably my favorite part of their relationship.
别太用力
我在军校为别人剃过一次头发
I did this once in military school --
最后那孩子不得不剃成光头
the kid had to shave his head.
你为什么告诉我这事
Why are you telling me that?
说真的  别太用力
Seriously, don't press so hard.
他们就像一对老夫老妻
They were like an old married couple --
他们很年轻  又是同性恋  却不爱外出消遣
they were young, gay, but they never wanted to go out.
我有时提议"我们去酒吧吧  我们去夜店吧"
I'm like, "let's go to the bar. Let's go to the club."
布兰登 好友
他们不太外出消遣
They didn't go out a lot,
因为他们总是在努力工作
'cause they were always working,
想方设法地构建自己的生活
trying to build something.
我知道对汤姆而言  这不仅是为了忠贞
I know that, for Tom, it wasn't just about fidelity,
当然  这很重要
which, of course, was like number one.
与此同时
It was also about being
他将自己的情感
completely emotionally available,
精神和灵魂都完全交给了谢恩
mentally available, spiritually available to Shane.
当你到了我这把岁数
When you get to my age,
会对一切抱有怀疑态度
you start being a little agnostic
比如感情那种事谁都说不准
that anything like that can occur.
但渐渐的  我能明显的看出
But over time, it became pretty apparent
他们之间的感情
that this was something that was probably going
可以维持很久很久
to last for a very, very long time.
他们围绕在一种与众不同的光环之中
There was an aura about them that just was something special.
乔什 好友
在场的每一位
Everyone in this room,
以及任何观看这部纪录片的人都会希望
or anyone watching this documentary could wish
能够拥有汤姆和谢恩这样的爱情
that they had the love that Tom and Shane had.
这是你每晚都梦寐以求的东西
That's what you dream about at night.
而他们得以美梦成真
And they had it.
谢恩和汤姆开始为一些乐手做在线推广
Shane and Tom started doing online promotion for musicians.
他们有个小小的工作室
And they had the little, tiny shack of a studio,
真是有趣极了
But it was just so much fun,
我们可以花上几小时的时间
and we would just spend hours and hours
尝试用各种方式来征服全世界
just trying to think of ways to take over the world.
突然之间
All of a sudden,
他们自制的一系列视频开始问世
there was this factory of videos that started coming out.
他们有个想法
They had all these ideas
那就是制作一档电视节目或旅游节目
for what could be a TV show or a travel show.
大家好  我是汤姆  正身处巴西里约热内卢
Hey, everybody, I'm Tom, in the beautiful,
这个美丽酷热又潮湿的城市
extremely hot and humid city of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.
欢迎访问汤谢网
Welcome to tomandshane.com.
-我是汤姆  -我是谢恩
- I'm Tom. - And I'm Shane.
我们在欧胡岛
And we're in Oahu.
你为什么总用这种嗓音说话
Why do you always do that voice?
乃们好  偶是飞行员
Hello, I'm the pilot.
偶比飞行员更腻害
This is better than a pilot.
你知道自己会这么说话吧
You know you do that voice.
-那必须滴  -好吧
- Oh, I know. - Okay.
他们成了冒险家
They became adventurers,
电影制片人  纪录片制作人
filmmakers, documentarians.
我觉得他们真的很喜欢这个想法
I think they just really liked the idea
拍下他们所经历的美好时光  并与世人分享
of taking the excitement that they had and sharing it.
我和汤姆越是相爱
The more Tom and I fell in love,
我们越想告诉我们的父母
the more we wanted to tell our parents about it.
但是我们有个想法
But each of us had the philosophy
在没有找到那个
that there was no need to tell your family
谢恩的姐妹
能够与你共度余生的伴侣之前
until you found that person
没必要告诉自己的家人
that you were gonna spend the rest of your life with.
我妈和阿姨来看我
So, my mom and my aunt were visiting,
那天已经很晚了
and it was very late at night,
但我跟我妈说我得和她谈谈
but I told my mom that I had to talk to her.
当着汤姆的面  我说"妈"
With Tom by my side, I said, "mom."
我说"亲爱的  如果你想告诉我你是同性恋"
I said, "honey, if you're gonna tell me you're gay,
"没关系  我知道这事  我可以接受"
that's fine. I know it, and I'm okay with it."
接着我问"汤姆是你的伴侣吗"
And I said, "and is Tom your partner?"
汤姆说"是的  我是他的伴侣"
And Tom goes, "yep. I'm his partner."
汤姆坐在那  本以为会有一场激烈的争吵
Tom was sitting there waiting for a big blowup or something,
而我只说了句  "太好了"
And I just said, "Well, great.
"我不用再像以前那样担心谢恩了"
You know, I don't have to worry about Shane like I did."
汤姆是上天赐予我的礼物
Tom was my godsend.
谢恩的焦虑症再也没发过
Shane didn't have his anxieties anymore.
他更有自信
He was more confident.
生活得很幸福
He was happy.
变得更像一个男子汉了
He was just more of a man.
我从没想过
I never imagined
我会比以前更爱我母亲
that I could love my mom even more than I did.
当我为自己是同性恋而挣扎时  她一直陪在我身边
She had been there through all my struggles of being gay.
我们从没有开诚布公地谈过这件事
And we never said out loud what the real deal was,
但现在终于说出来了
but now we had.
那感觉真的好极了
It was the greatest feeling ever.
演唱: 汤姆
我和汤姆知道
Tom and I knew
向他父母坦白会是个巨大的挑战
it would be a challenge to come out to his parents.
他去印第安纳州过圣诞节
So, he was in Indiana for Christmas.
当时只有他和他母亲两个人
It was just him and his mom.
电视上播放了一档
And there was something that came on TV
关于女同情侣的节目
about a lesbian couple,
汤姆的母亲说那太恶心了
And Tom's mom made a comment about how that was disgusting.
就在那时  汤姆意识到
And Tom, at that moment, just realized,
"我得告诉她真相"
"Like, I need to tell her."
他对他母亲说  "妈  我是同性恋"
He told his mom, "Mom, I'm gay.
"你说那样的话  其实也在说我"
When you say things like that, you're talking about me."
我觉得他以为事情会像
He was, I think, sort of building
谢恩出柜时一样
on what had happened when Shane came out.
谢恩向他母亲坦白的时候
Shane had come out to his mother,
她母亲已经猜得八九不离十
and she basically filled in the blanks --
"你是同性恋  我早知道了"
"Oh, you're gay. I knew that already.
"我一直都知道"
I always knew that."
我一直以为他母亲知道他是同性恋
I was sure that his mom knew that he was gay.
但她立马给他父亲打了电话
But she immediately called his dad
让他下班回家
to come home from work
就因为这条令人震惊的消息
because of this breaking news.
她一直不停地说
And she went on and on
这是罪过
about how it was a sin
说汤姆应该早点告诉他们
and that Tom should have told them sooner
这样就可以带他接受治疗
so he could have gotten medical help.
他父亲对他说了一些很难听的话
His dad said a lot of hateful things towards him
他怪谢恩把他儿子变成了同性恋
and blamed Shane for making him gay.
"都是谢恩的错  他让你变成了同性恋"
"It's Shane's fault. Shane turned you gay.
"在洛杉矶生活让你变成了同性恋"
Being in L.A. Turned you gay."
"你所有的成就都变得一文不值"
"All of your accomplishments so far mean nothing now."
他们说  "你得改变想法  你必须改变想法"
They said, "Change your mind. You have to change your mind."
汤姆一直说不
And Tom said that he just kept saying no --
他说  "我改变不了"
Like, you know, "I can't change my mind.
"这是没法改变的事"
It's not a mind-change thing."
汤姆打电话给我
Tom called me.
说他父亲拿枪指着他
He told me that his dad pulled a shotgun on him.
当时我非常害怕
And at that point, I was really scared.
我俩通电话的时候
So, while Tom and I were on the phone,
他父亲诺曼把门从门框上扯了下来
His dad, Norman, literally ripped the door off the hinges.
他母亲拿起电话对我说
And his mom got on the phone, and she said to me,
"听着  你个狗娘养的"
"Listen here, fucker --
"我不知道你对我儿子做了什么"
I don't know what you did to our son,
"但我们会去洛杉矶  把你揪出来"
but we're gonna come to L.A., and we're gonna find you."
我记得他父亲说的原话是
I think the phrase his dad used was,
他要去加州把他的肠子扯出来
He was gonna come out to California and gut him.
我以前总有这样的幻想
I used to always have this fantasy
我和汤姆去印第安纳过圣诞节
of Tom and I going to Indiana for Christmas
一同进入梦乡
and just, you know, going to bed
汤姆的家庭录像
然后在圣诞节早晨醒来
and waking up on Christmas morning,
大家聚在客厅里
all of us going out to the living room --
客厅里有棵圣诞树
You know, there's the tree,
我和汤姆跟他家人坐在一起
and Tom and I just sitting there with his family,
一起拆开礼物
opening presents together,
我会说一些我觉得有趣的事情
and me just saying something that I think's funny,
放眼望去  汤姆的父母在开怀大笑
and I look over, and Tom's parents are laughing.
我知道这想法很蠢  但是...
It's stupid, but it's just...
如果真能梦想成真
It would be like an incredible thing
那该多好啊
if something like that happened.
警察赶到家里的时候
When the police showed up at the house,
汤姆的父亲不屑一顾地说
Tom's dad just kind of pooh-poohed it off, and he said,
"你知道那些加州小孩是什么德性"
"Ah, you know how these California kids are."
之后两天的电话
Those phone calls for those next two days,
直到汤姆离开那之前  真的是...
until Tom got out of there, were just...
这两个孩子都让我心疼极了
My heart just broke for both of those boys.
真是太可怕  太让人难过了
It was just so scary and so sad.
第二天一早
So, that next morning,
汤姆的父母在厨房里
Tom's parents were in the kitchen
桌子上放着一本圣经
with a bible on the table.
他们大声诵读里面的篇章
Out loud, they were saying the verses,
圣经说教开始了
他们正在找对应的篇章
像是在为昨天发生的事找理由
almost, in a way, just to justify that, the day before,
我为他们祈祷
汤姆  真心的
他们打了他们的儿子  只因为他是同性恋
they beat up their son because he was gay.
他说  "我真不敢相信"
He's like, "I can't believe this.
糟透了...
我不小心咬了我妈
"我竟然被打了  他们还说"
"I just got attacked and told
"我应该把我是同性恋这件事"
"that I should have taken the fact that I'm gay
"带进坟墓里"
to the grave."
我父亲从未如此害怕我
我看见他眼里的恐惧  我差点杀了他
情况很糟糕
It was just an awful situation,
于是汤姆尽快离开了
and Tom, you know, got out of there as soon as he could
飞回了加利福尼亚
and flew back to California.
最后玛莎还是来了加州
So, eventually, Martha made her way out to California,
我非常非常紧张
and I was really, really nervous.
这是自那次糟糕的经历后
This was like the first time that I was going to see Martha
我第一次见到玛莎
since that, you know, horrible experience.
我觉得玛莎之所以来这
I think Martha came here
是因为她不想失去她的儿子
because she did not want to lose her son.
所以她必须接受谢恩
So she had to embrace Shane
表现出她似乎接受了这段感情
and act like she accepted the relationship.
开始有点尴尬
It was a little awkward for awhile.
但渐渐地  我们熟起来了
But, eventually, you know, we warmed up to each other.
我们一起去吃晚餐
We would go to dinner.
汤姆跟她一起歇斯底里地笑
Tom and her would laugh, like, hysterically.
他俩在一起时
When they get together,
就像两个小老太太
it's like two little, old ladies.
尽管她没有明说
And although she didn't say, like, you know,
"谢恩  对不起"  或是  "汤姆  对不起"
"Shane, I'm sorry," or, "Tom, I'm sorry
"我们之前不该那么对你"
for how we handled everything,"
对我们来说  她是在用自己的方式
To us, it was like this is her way
表示她接受我们了
of showing that she's accepting us.
她不仅爱她儿子  她真的爱死他儿子了
It wasn't that she loved her son -- she loved her son.
她会不惜一切代价接近他
And whatever it took to be near him, she did.
哪怕去耕地她都愿意
If she had to push a plow, she would,
只要能接近她的儿子
just to be near her son.
这张照片是他们去格劳曼剧院的时候拍的
She has this picture where they went to Grauman theatre
当时还看了埃尔维斯的手印
and saw Elvis' handprints.
她说那是她一生中最快乐的日子
She said that was the happiest day of her life.
我觉得她很享受在加州的生活
I think she truly enjoyed coming out to California.
然后她回到印第安纳之后
And then she would get back to Indiana,
又基本上全盘否定汤姆在这的生活
and, basically, wouldn't acknowledge Tom's life here.
进展就像婴儿学步一样缓慢
And, you know, again, it was kind of like just baby steps.
几次之后
Truly, after like a few times,
我们觉得她接受了我们
we felt like she was okay with us
她为我们高兴
and she was happy for us.
她还坚持让我和汤姆睡卧室
She even insisted on Tom and me taking the bedroom
她和我们的狗一起睡沙发
while she stayed on the sofa with our dog.
汤姆的声音
贾斯汀  你怎么能这样
Justin. I can't believe you.
看着我
Look at me.
你怎么忍心
How could you...
留我独守空闺
leave me all alone?
好吧  我想你  可你只想和她待在一起
Okay, I miss you, and you just want to stay with her.
你这个叛徒
You're such a traitor.
没错  低头忏悔去吧
Yeah. You put that head down.
汤姆很喜欢他的狗
Tom was obsessed with his dog.
总是给它拍照片
Tom was always, always taking pictures of him.
就像是他的亲生宝宝
It was like someone with, like, a newborn baby.
它被遗弃在好莱坞的一辆车底下
He was actually found abandoned under a car in Hollywood.
你好啊  拿破仑  最近过得好吗
Hi, Napoleon. How are you?
它有一套圣诞老人的衣服
He had a Santa Claus outfit,
还有些其他稀奇古怪的服饰
and he had some other crazy outfit.
我就想  "天呐"
And I thought, "Oh, my god.
"这不会是两个同性恋人"
"This is not gonna be two gay boys
"和他们的基情小狗吧"
with their gay, little dog, is it?"
果不其然  很快Facebook上
And sure enough -- pretty quick, on Facebook,
汤姆就上传了
Tom was taking pictures
贾斯汀·鲍比身着小雨衣的照片
of Justin Bobby in his little rain gear.
我当时想  "我的天  你们这两个家伙"
And I thought, "Oh, my God. You guys, come on.
"别闹了"
You got to quit that."
除了结婚和组建家庭之外
Another dream that Tom and I had,
我和汤姆还有一个梦想
aside from wanting to be married and have a family,
那就是一起环游世界
was we wanted to travel the world together.
我们的目标是游遍世界各大奇观
And our goal was to hit all the wonders of the world.
汤姆去世之前  我们去成了四个
And we managed to make it to four before Tom died.
♪沿着尼罗河畔看金字塔
♪ See the pyramids along the Nile
♪在热带岛屿上看日出
♪ Watch the sunrise from a tropic isle
他们很享受生活
They enjoyed living.
他们一起旅行时  让我惊讶的是
When they traveled together, that's what would just amaze me,
♪亲爱的你要记得
♪ Just remember darling all the while
他们去过埃及  秘鲁  伦敦和巴黎
where they went to Egypt and to Peru and London and Paris.
♪你是我的专属
♪ You belong to me
汤姆和谢恩之所以能负担得起这些旅行
The way Tom and Shane were able to afford these trips is
首先是因为他们很节俭
they're, first of all, very frugal,
谢恩在我们这干活
and not only did Shane work the job that he did for us,
♪在老城集市中游荡
♪ See the market place in old Algier
而汤姆也会打些零工
Tom would work, you know, get extra jobs
♪为我寄来照片和纪念品
♪ Send me photographs and souvenirs
拍摄广告之类的
doing commercials or whatever
因此他们可以去那些地方旅行
so they could travel to all these places.
他们坐的不是头等舱
And they didn't go first class.
♪坠入梦乡时你要记得
♪ Just remember when a dream appears
而是像学生一样旅游
They would travel like they were students.
我记得他们第一次旅行是去埃及
The first trip I remember them taking was to Egypt,
沿尼罗河而下
down the Nile.
♪你是我的专属
♪ You belong to me
但那并不是我会选择的旅行方式
But it wasn't the kind of trip that I would have gone on.
♪没有你我是如此孤单
♪ I'd be so alone without you
他们睡在用屏风隔开的甲板上
They slept on the deck with canvas dividers,
盖着毯子
covered in blankets,
汤姆还得了肺炎
and Tom caught pneumonia,
但他们真的度过了一段美好时光
but they had one heck of a good time.
♪或许你也会孤单沮丧
♪ Maybe you'd be lonesome too and blue
♪在回家之前你要记得
♪ Just remember till you're home again
♪你是我的专属
♪ You belong to me
我和汤姆进展到
Tom and I reached a point where
他准备跟我回蒙大拿州的阶段
we were ready for him to come to Montana.
我总跟他说蒙大拿州有多美
You know, I kept talking about how beautiful Montana is.
但对于我来说  更激动的是
But for me, it was more about -- you know, I was just excited
他终于要见我家人了
for him to finally meet my entire family.
我的父亲  干了一辈子伐木工
My dad, all his life, was a logger.
他会开同性恋的玩笑
I mean, he told gay jokes --
不是那种可以跟他坐下来说
not the type of person that you could sit down and be like,
"喂  你儿子是同性恋"之后
"Hey, your son's gay,"
他还能坦然接受的那种人
and he would take it easily.
第一次见到汤姆时
The first time I ever met Tom,
我刚从镇上回来
I had just been to town,
看到我女儿的车停在车道上
and I had seen my daughter's car in the driveway.
谢恩和汤姆赶紧躲进了柜子
So Shane and Tom jumped in the closet to hide,
杰西 谢恩的姐姐
我爸走进来时
and then my dad walks in,
他俩就一起跳出来大喊 "想不到吧"
and they both jump out of the closet like, "Surprise!"
结果是我的儿子和他的伴侣
And here's my boy, and here's his partner.
他们成功了  我确实没想到
And it worked -- they surprised me.
我们都觉得这真是太搞笑了
And we just thought it was funnier than hell that they did that,
因为他们真是从柜子里跳出来"出柜"的
because it's like they came out of the closet at my dad's house.
汤姆知道我有大男子主义
Tom, he knew I was a macho-type guy,
我可能会有大男子主义的保守观念
and maybe that I was gonna have the macho-type conservatism
认为我不会接纳他
that wouldn't accept him,
你能够看得出他为此花的心思
and you could just see he tried all the time around me.
我很感激他做的努力
And I appreciated that -- him trying,
努力让自己变得讨喜
him trying to be likeable.
喜欢上汤姆是件很容易的事
It was easy to like Tom.
他是一个很棒的小伙子
He was a great guy.
汤姆很有魅力
Tom was a pistol.
他是个很有趣的人
He was so much fun to be around.
我见过他逗谢恩大笑
I saw that he made Shane laugh.
那种快乐是你在
It's the type of happiness you have
遇到灵魂伴侣后才会有的
when you meet your soul mate.
这让我之前的担心云消雾散
And that made all my worries just disappear.
汤姆跟我回亚利桑那州看望我的祖父母
So, Tom and I went to Arizona to visit my grandparents.
谢恩非常开心
Shane was so happy.
这是他长大之后
It was the happiest that I'd ever seen him,
我见他最开心的一次
since he was a little kid on up.
我的曾祖母帕特也在
And my Great-grandma Pat was there.
没人告诉她我跟汤姆是情侣
And no one told Grandma Pat that Tom and I were a couple.
她说  "很高兴见到你啊"
She was like, "Oh, nice to meet you."
之后  我听到她在另一间房里
And then, later, I heard her in the other room
问我的祖母朱迪  "那人是谁啊"
ask my Grandma Judy like, "So, who was that guy?"
我不知道谢恩是同性恋
Well, I never knew Shane was gay,
但当我见到他伴侣时
but I met his partner,
我觉得他是个不错的小伙子
and he was a very nice guy,
大家都很喜欢他  我觉得没什么
and we all liked him and went along fine with it.
汤姆迷上帕特祖母是有原因的
Tom was fascinated with Grandma Pat for a few reasons.
每一年  她都会记录自己杀了多少条蛇
You know, every year, she keeps track of how many snakes she kills.
我总是跟蛇过不去
Well, I'm always after a snake --
我不希望它们出现在附近
I don't want them around.
你每年春天最多能杀多少条蛇来着
I mean, you killed up to how many in a spring -- every spring?
能有40条甚至更多
Oh, I killed up to 40 or better.
有一次我和汤姆陪两个祖母去散步
After Tom and I went for a walk with both of my grandmas,
在回家的路上
when we were coming back into the house,
帕特祖母搂着汤姆
Grandma Pat like put her arm around Tom.
她说  "欢迎加入这个大家庭"
She was like, "Welcome to the family."
她已经九十岁了
She's 90 years old,
但仍然能接纳了我们的关系
and, you know, she's accepting our relationship.
对他们品头论足的那些人
People that talk about them,
他们对此一知半解
they don't understand a lot of it.
他们认为  如果他俩去教堂
And they think that, if they go to church and everything,
上帝自会惩罚他们
that God will take care of it --
就像惩罚其他同性恋一样
They can be just like all the rest of the guys.
所以你没法说服他们
And so you can't get through to them.
说实话  那些话我都听腻了
To tell you the truth, I'm tired of hearing about it --
他们的确不是罗密欧与茱丽叶
So they're not Romeo and Juliet.
没错  他们是罗密欧与罗密欧
That's right -- they're Romeo and Romeo.
多大事啊
Get over it.
我不喜欢在公共场合表露自己的情感
I did not like to show any public display of affection --
即便是坐在飞机上
Whether it would be us on a plane flying somewhere,
我们想亲热时
and we wanted to be affectionate,
会用大衣或是毯子遮住手臂
we would actually take a coat or a blanket and cover our arms,
然后在毯子下紧握双手
and like hold hands under the blanket.
不要太明显啦
我认为谢恩很在意他们所处的场合
I think that Shane was very conscious of where they were
不想让别人感到不舒服
and not making other people uncomfortable.
我从不会当着朋友或其他人的面
I never really wanted to say, "I love you"
说"我爱你"
in front of friends or anyone.
所以我俩就发明了个小暗号
So we developed this little code --
无论在晚宴或是派对上
Whether we're at like a dinner or a party,
其中一人会设法敲三下桌子
one of us would find a way just to tap the table three times
以此代替"我爱你"
just to say, "I love you."
因此  这个声音对我俩来说很特殊
So, that became a very special sound for both of us.
汤姆热情洋溢
Tom was just so passionate,
他的满腔爱意
and he was so affectionate
在一定程度上慢慢瓦解了谢恩的心理障碍
that it sort of brought Shane out of his shell a little bit,
柯琳 朋友
使他在大庭广众之下
as far as, you know, being out in public
不会因此而感到羞愧或难堪
and not being ashamed or embarrassed that,
敢于大声喊出  "没错  这是我的伴侣  我们是同性恋"
you know, "Yeah, this is my partner, and we're gay."
"那又如何"
"So what?"
谢恩的视频日记
有一次  我们在巴黎
Once, we were in Paris,
我们站在埃菲尔铁塔前
and we were in front of the Eiffel Tower,
我突然想  "去他妈的"
I just decided like, "Screw it --
"我就要偷偷亲他一下"  我真这么做了
I'm just gonna sneak in a kiss," and I did.
汤姆的表情像是在说  "刚才发生了什么"
Tom's face -- he was just like, "What just happened?"
他非常激动
He was so excited.
但亲完之后我俩的第一个反应是
But then the first thing we did after the kiss,
"有被人看到吗"  四处张望
we like looked around, like, "Did anyone see us?"
但我很高兴这么做
But I'm so happy that I did that
因为他欣喜若狂
'cause he was just thrilled.
汤姆想和谢恩结婚
Tom wanted to marry Shane,
但他想要真正合法的婚姻
but he wanted it to be legal.
而不是所谓"原则上合法"的说辞
He wasn't gonna settle for a technicality,
或是"现在还算合法  但明天就说不准了"
or an, "Oh, it happens to be legal right this minute,
这种自欺欺人的态度
but tomorrow it could not be."
他是那种有担当的男人
He was the kind of man that just stood up for things,
我觉得在他的内心深处
and I think part of it
他是想向家里所有人表态
was like he wanted to show everyone back home that,
"我是认真的  这就是我"
"I'm serious. This is me."
圣诞快乐
爱你直到海枯石烂
爱你的汤姆
他买了个戒指作为我的圣诞礼物
He bought me a ring for Christmas,
我们曾约定不在对方身上花钱
and we had agreed to not spend any money on each other.
他对我说  "谢恩肯定会生我气的"
He would tell me, "But Shane's gonna get mad,
"我们是有预算的"
"because we have a budget,
"但我真的很想送个给他"
"but I just want to get it for him so bad."
我打开包装  是个戒指
And I opened it, and it was a ring
还有一张纸条  上面写着
with a note in it that said,
"2011年将会永远改变我们的生活"
"2011 will change our lives forever.
谢谢你给我的爱
若不是你我早已迷失自己
我有预感  2011年将会永远改变我们的生活
爱你到海枯石烂
汤姆
"爱你的汤姆"
Love, Tom."
我曾幻想过他们结婚时的场景
I had the image of their wedding played out in my head.
我知道这一天迟早会到来
I knew it was gonna happen someday.
毋庸置疑的是
There was no question
他们想要和对方共度余生
that they wanted to spend the rest of their lives together
并组建家庭
and have a family.
这正是他所渴求的
That was something he wanted so bad.
他过去常说
He used to say,
"我好想要个小汤姆跑来跑去"
"You know, I'd love to have a little Thomas running around."
我在思考谢恩和汤姆的故事时
And I guess one of the saddest parts,
我觉得最令人伤心的部分是
when I really think about Shane and Tom, is the fact that,
他们基本上实现了"美国梦"
essentially, they were living the American dream,
除了他们没法结婚这条
with the exception of being able to get married to each other.
当然很多人会提到"同居伴侣"这个概念
Well, everyone, like, brings up domestic partnership,
这在某种程度上挺令我气愤的
and it angers me in a way,
因为任何小姑娘都不会坐在自己的房间里
because no little girl is sitting in her room
幻想着说
and saying that,
"我等不及想要个同居伴侣"
"I can't wait to have a domestic partnership.
"我等不及在同居期间穿上婚纱"
"I can't wait to wear a white dress during my domestic partnership."
这不是大家梦想中的事情
That's not something that people dream about.
大家梦想的是结婚
They dream about getting married.
而他们却没法结婚
And they weren't allowed to do that.
即使现在同性婚姻合法了
And if it is ever legal,
他俩也无法步入婚姻殿堂
they'll never be able to experience it,
因为他已经不在了
because he's not here anymore.
我很庆幸在汤姆去世前的那周三见过他一面
I was lucky to see Tom the Wednesday before he died.
♪慢慢靠近边缘
♪ Getting closer to the edge
♪我若坠落  会否有人将我接住
♪ if I fall, will someone catch me
然后我们聊起了谢恩
And we talked about, you know, Shane,
他说  "我懂得了什么才是真正的爱情"
and he said, "I learned what love really is.
"我小时候脑子里只是有这样一个想法"
I used to have this idea in my head when I was young,
"而现在同谢恩在一起"
and being with Shane, I've learned
"我从生活的点点滴滴中体会到了真爱"
what it really looks like on a daily basis,
"这比我想象中还要丰富许多"
and it's so much more than I ever thought possible."
这首歌的名字叫做《我若坠落》
That's what the song's called -- "If I fall."
♪纵使我坠落
♪ Even if I fall
-谢谢  谢谢  -不用客气
- Thank you for that. - You're very welcome.
好吧  那就这样
All right. So, there you go.
《我若坠落》
"If I fall",
我们都同意这个歌名  好吧
are we agreeing that's what we're gonna call the song? All right.
2011年5月7日
现在令我不安的是  那天早上我们吵了一架
The thing that haunts me now is we had a fight that morning.
我真是服了你了
我们必须说清楚  不能总粘在一起
本来我们是要和我们的朋友艾丽克斯出去玩的
Originally, we were supposed to hang out with our friend Alex,
然后一起照些照片
and go take photographs together.
我等了好久才盼来今天  我很生气
我们争执过后
And after our little argument,
我决定留在家里
I decided that I would just stay home.
我和汤姆决定在工作室见面
Tom and I decided to meet at the studio.
我们商量了好久
And we kept going back and forth.
然后他说  "我们去你家吧"
And he was like, "Let's go to your place.
"我突然想起了你家厨房的灿烂阳光"
"I just remember the sunlight in the kitchen.
"我现在需要那样的阳光"
I need some of that sunlight now."
我说  "没问题"
And I was like, "Okay."
他说  "不  我想为你做些事情"
He was like, "No, I want to do something good for you.
"我们去拍照吧  这会让心情好起来的"
Let's do a photo shoot. It'll turn this day around."
我刚开始跟一个男生约会
So, I had just started dating this man,
那天是他的生日  可我没去陪他
and it was his birthday, and I wasn't with him,
汤姆说  "我就是想让他吃醋"
so Tom was like, "I want to make him jealous,
"我们把你的照片发到Facebook上去"
so let's put pictures of you on facebook."
他一直在喊  "来拍嘛  来拍嘛"
And he was the one that was like, "Let's do it. Let's do it."
"我可以给你做发型吗"
"Hey, can I do your hair?"
我说  "好吧"
I was like, "Um, okay."
然后我往胸罩里塞满了袜子
And I have, you know, my brassiere filled with socks,
因为...  我并没那么丰满
'cause, you know, there's just not much there.
汤姆  我爱你胜过一切  真的
汤姆一整天都在跟我发信息
So, Tom and I were texting throughout the day.
我爱你  谢恩
我们最终和好了
And we eventually made up.
我们根本没讨论去不去屋顶
It wasn't even a discussion whether or not to go to the roof,
因为我们经常到屋顶上去
because we always went to the roof.
我们在短信里说深爱着对方
And we told each other that we love each other.
我很欣慰我们和好了
And I'm so thankful that we did,
因为这已成了我永恒的回忆
'cause I have that forever now.
我们去屋顶的时候
And so, by the time we get up to the roof,
汤姆拿着他的照相机
Tom has his camera.
他准备就绪了
He's all ready.
我们差不多上去过50多次
We'd all been up there like 50 times,
但每次我都很害怕
and every time, I'm just paranoid.
因为护栏其实不高
'cause it's not like a tall wall.
是很矮的那种
It's a short wall.
他就拿着相机各种拍
He was just playing around with the camera,
我知道他同时也在给谢恩发信息
and, meanwhile, I know that he had just been texting to Shane.
不要靠近边缘
我告诉他别跑到边上去
I told him to stay away from the edge,
我可不是开玩笑  汤姆
因为我们都知道他是个笨手笨脚的人
'cause we all know that he's a klutz.
他回复我说
And he even wrote back.
"哈哈  我不会的"  好像我在跟他开玩笑
He was like, "Ha-ha! I will" Like, I was joking.
我说  "汤姆  我是认真的"
And I said, "Tom, I'm serious.
"别跑到边上去"
Like, stay away from the edge."
他照了几张照片
So, he takes a bunch of pictures.
我尽量表现得风骚
I'm trying to be as slutty --
不是性感  因为确实不性感
You know, not sexy, 'cause it wasn't sexy.
我在屋顶的一个角落  然后我们换了位置
I'm in one corner, and then we suddenly switch.
他说  "我拍到了  我拍到了"
And he's like, " I've got it! I've got it!"
然后他往后退了三四步
So, he takes like three or four steps back.
汤姆为艾丽克斯拍的最后一张照片
谁都想不到他会掉下去
I don't think it registered that he was gonna fall.
他当时看起来像这样  而我则是这样
He was like, "Ha-ha!" And I was like, "Ohh."
然后我看着他
You know, and I looked at him,
当时的感觉就是  "天呐"
And it was like we both thought, "Oh, no.
"谢恩会气死的"
Shane's gonna be so mad."
好像他知道了我们离边缘这么近一样
You know, just like if he knew that we were that close.
之后  便是一场噩梦的开始
And then, after that, it was a nightmare.
我甚至没去边上往下看
I didn't even go look over the edge.
我把鞋子一扔  跑下楼去
I just, like, threw my shoes on, ran downstairs.
我的手机在后兜里
I had my phone in my back pocket,
我拨了911  但什么都听不到
And I dialed 911, but I couldn't hear.
所以我就把手机给了走廊里的人
So I just gave it to somebody out in the hallway,
因为大家听到他坠楼的动静
'cause people heard him.
我收到艾丽克斯的短信说汤姆掉下去了
I received a text from Alex to tell me that Tom had fallen.
汤姆掉下去了
我以为这是个玩笑  "这不可能是真的"
And I thought it was a joke -- "There's no way this is real."
所以我回复她说  "这一点也不好笑"
So I texted her back, and I said, "That's not funny."
汤姆掉下去了
说真的  别乱开玩笑
之后我没再收到她的回复
And then I didn't hear back from her.
于是我打了汤姆的手机
And so then I called Tom's phone,
但没人接
and no one picked up.
就在那时  我开始着急了
So at that moment is when my heart just started racing.
我跑到楼下的时候  他趴在地上
By the time I got there, he's on, you know, his stomach.
我抚摸着他的背
And I'm rubbing his back.
我说  "没事的  汤米  没事的"
And I'm saying, "It's okay, Tommy. It's okay, Tommy."
而我穿的像个妓女
Meanwhile, I look like a total hooker.
救护车过了好久才到
But it takes forever for the ambulance to get there.
差不多过了有25分钟吧
I want to say 25 minutes later.
他们问我  "你有他的身份证件吗"
They were like, "Do you have his I.D.?
"你有他的身份证件吗"
Do you have his I.D.?"
我说  "身份证有那么重要吗"
And I was like, "What the fuck does it matter?!
"赶紧把他抬上救护车呀"
Just get him on the ambulance!"
我赶到急诊室
So, I got to the E.R.,
他们把我带到艾丽克斯的房间
and they took me into a room where Alex was,
她情绪很激动
and she was hysterical.
我一看到谢恩
And when I first saw Shane,
我说  "要是坠楼的是我就好了"
I said, "I wish it were me."
我说  "因为你们拥有彼此"
I said, "Because you two have each other,
"你俩爱得那么死去活来"
"and the love you have is so strong,
"我真希望掉下去的是我"
I wish it had been me who fell over."
我问她  "现在是什么状况"
I asked her, you know, "Well, what's happening?
"他们还在抢救吗"  我完全不知情
are they working on him?" I didn't know anything.
她也一无所知
And she didn't know anything.
我们抱在一起  说爱着对方
We hugged, you know, and we said we loved each other.
我仍抱有希望  觉得他会没事的
And I was still hanging on to hope that he was okay.
我试着给谢恩打电话
I tried calling Shane,
但总联系不上他
and I couldn't get through to him.
后来  他终于给我回了电话
And, finally, he calls me back.
他说  "妈  汤姆去拍照"
He said, "Mom, Tom was doing a photo shoot,
"从屋顶上坠楼了"
and he fell off the roof."
我说  "天呐"
And I just -- "Oh, my god."
我说  "亲爱的  要一直祈祷"
I said, "Honey, just keep on praying.
"他会没事的  咱们都会为他祈祷的"
He'll be fine. You know, we'll get the prayers going here."
我收到谢恩的短信说
I got a text message from Shane saying,
"米凯拉  求你快祈祷  汤姆受伤了"
"Michaela, please pray -- Tom's hurt."
我立刻跪在地上  开始祈祷
And I immediately got down and started praying.
过了一会儿  他打给我
So, a little bit later, he calls me,
他说  "妈  他们不让我进去看他"
and he says, "Mom, they won't let me in to see him."
我问  "怎么会这样"
And I said, "Well, how come?"
他们说  "因为我不是他的家属"
And they said, "Because I'm not family."
我说  "天呐  谢恩"
And I just -- "Oh, my God, Shane."
于是我打给了汤姆的母亲
So, I called Tom's mom.
那时印第安纳州已是深夜
And it's, you know, late at night in Indiana.
她一开口便问道
And, you know, the first thing she says was,
"他喝了多少酒  谢恩"
"Well, how much was he drinking, Shane?"
我能听到他爸在后面说
And then his dad, in the background, was saying,
"他跑到屋顶上去做什么"
"Well, what the hell was he doing on the roof?"
随后  我就把电话给了
And I just, from that point forward, I made sure
在场的医护人员  让他们说了情况
to let the nursing staff or the doctors speak to her and to him.
等了差不多一小时之后
And it had been probably about an hour later,
医生来到我们的房间
the doctor came into the room,
我立马就知道了
and, like, I just, I knew.
我知道他要说些什么
Like, I knew what he was gonna say.
当他开始讲话的时候
And when he was talking,
我跟本什么都没听进去
like, it wasn't registering in my head.
好像左耳进右耳出
Like, I wasn't processing what he said.
他说他没挺过来
He just said he didn't make it.
真的非常...
And it was very, you know...
我们都失声痛哭
And we all just lost it.
我必须离开那个房间  因为我真得听不下去
I had to just leave the room because I couldn't hear it.
艾丽克斯一直在哭  她不停地做这个动作
Alex was crying, and she was continually doing this --
我想她受了很大的打击
I think because she was just so traumatized.
艾丽克斯的妈妈不停的说  "天呐"
And Alex's Mom was saying, "Oh, my god."
"天呐"
"Oh, my god."
或是  "他可怜的妈妈"
And sometimes she would say, "Oh, his mother."
因为第二天就是母亲节
'Cause Mother's Day was the next day.
于是我走出房间
So, I went outside.
给我妈打了电话
I called my mom, and...
我说  "妈  他走了"
And I was like, "Mom, he died."
她说  "我很遗憾  谢恩"
And, you know, she just said, "I'm so sorry, Shane.
"真的很遗憾"
I'm so sorry."
他一直在哭  我也在哭
And he was just crying, and I'm crying.
但再一次  你却在2400公里之外
And, you know, here you are, again, 1,500 miles away,
无法陪着自己的孩子
and you can't be there for your child.
我接到了他的电话
I got ahold of him,
说汤姆在医院里去世了
and Tom had just died in the hospital, and...
我永远不想再回忆这个时刻
I don't know. It's not a moment I want to ever go through again.
没有什么比这更痛苦
The worst pain I have ever felt in my heart.
我的脑子一片空白
Like, I just sunk.
我说  "你他妈开玩笑吧"
I just said, "Are you fucking kidding me?
"真的吗"  我说  "真的吗  谁会这样死掉"
Seriously?" I said, "Seriously, who dies like that?"
我以为在他断气的瞬间
I figured Shane was probably there when he passed,
谢恩会陪在他床边  紧握他的手
by his bed, holding his hand.
他却说没有
And he said no.
于是我冲向护士站  我说
So, I went to the nurse's station, and I said,
"我朋友的男朋友在这"
"You know, my friend's boyfriend is here.
"他刚刚去世  能让他们见最后一面吗"
He just passed away. Can you take him back?"
她却说  "在他父母来这之前"
And she said, "We can't allow non-family members to see him
"所有非亲属都不能见他"
until his parents arrive."
于是我一直和护士争论
So I kept trying to argue with this nurse.
那位女士说  "亲爱的  我理解你的心情"
And the lady was like, "I understand, honey, I do.
"但这有违医院规定"
But it's against the hospital rules.
"他不是他的家属"  我说  "他就是他的家属"
He's not his family." I said, "But he is his family.
"他们拥有一栋房子  拥有共同的事业"
They have a house together. They have a business together.
"他们还有一条狗"
They have a dog together.
"他们在一起六年了"
They've been together for six years."
最后  我们坐在一个房间里
Finally, we were sitting a the room,
一位护士打开房门
and this one nurse opened the door,
她问  "谢恩在这吗"
and she said, "Is Shane in here?"
于是我们走出房间
And so we went outside,
她拿着汤姆的驾驶证
and she was holding Tom's license,
她说  "天呐  他真是个帅小伙"
And she said, "Man, he was a good-looking guy. Geez.
"所有护士都在谈论他是多么的帅气"
And all the nurses back here are talking about how handsome he was,
"我们刚才在努力让他恢复..."
and we've been working back here to try to kind of...
"恢复成你记忆中的样子"
make him look the way that you remember him.
"跟我来  我们带你去见他"
Come with me. We're gonna take you back."
我想  护士们最终弄明白了
I think, at the end of the day, the nurses knew,
无论是同性恋
you know, it's not a gay thing.
还是异性恋
It's not a straight thing.
不变的是爱情
It's a human thing.
但那些护士给谢恩的
But it was definitely a gift, I think,
绝对是上天的恩赐
that those women gave to Shane.
于是我们来到了他病房
So, they walked back to his room.
他浑身插满了管子
There was tubes all over his body,
管子直接插进他的胸部
tubes coming out of his chest.
他的脸被盖了起来  但你仍能看到
His face was covered, but you could see that
他的脸上满是血迹
there, you know, had been blood, like, all around his face.
我感觉这不是真的
And it didn't really seem like this was happening.
我在旁边站了一会儿
I just stood there for a while.
不知道该做什么
I didn't know what to do.
他全身上下我唯一能碰的地方
But the only place that I could put my hand
就是他的腿
was like on his leg.
于是最后一次  我在他腿上敲了三下
And I did, you know, one final "Tap, tap, tap."
♪今晨醒来
♪ I woke up this morning
♪惊闻噩耗
♪ And I heard the news
♪心碎滋味  五味杂陈
♪ I know the pain of a heartbreak
♪我心迷茫
♪ I don't have answers
♪你也一样
♪ And neither do you
♪心碎滋味  五味杂陈
♪ I know the pain of a heartbreak
♪人死难复生
♪ This isn't easy
♪痛苦亦迷茫
♪ This isn't clear
♪心碎已至此
♪ And you don't need Jesus
♪上苍难回天
♪ Till you're here
♪一切迷茫及困惑
♪ Oh, the confusion and the doubts you had
♪至此皆逝
♪ Up and walk away
♪随风飘逝
♪ They walk awa-a-a-y
♪心碎已至此
♪ When a heart breaks
昨晚在洛斯费利兹区
A man fell to his death
意外坠亡
一名男士从四层高的公寓上
from a four-story apartment building
意外坠亡
in Los Feliz last night.
警方称他当时在为一名女士拍照
Police say he was taking pictures of a woman.
警方排除了他杀可能
They don't suspect foul play,
称之为令人心痛的意外
and are calling his death a tragic accident.
死者是一名演员兼电视主持人
He was an actor and TV host.
我想不起汤姆去世后的那段日子是怎么过的
The days after Tom passed away are kind of a blur.
我只想让家人
There was nothing I wanted more
陪在我身边
than just to have my family there with me.
尽管我的父母离婚了
And so it really meant a lot
但他们还是说
that my parents, although they're divorced,
"我们都会来陪你的"
that they were able to just say,
这对我意义重大
"Look, like, we're gonna be there for you."
我的姐妹们也说要来
And my sisters were going to, as well.
我和我爸从艾丽克斯家里开回了汤姆的车
My dad and I, we went to go pick up Tom's car at Alex's place.
在回家的路上
And during the car ride home,
我们第一次讨论了我是同性恋这件事
we talked about me being gay for the first time.
我想让他知道
I wanted him to know,
尽管他出柜后我什么也没说
even though I had never said anything since he'd come out,
但我全心全意地接受他
that I fully accepted him.
我们甚至讨论了汤姆爸爸的感受
I think we even talked about how Tom's dad must feel,
因为汤姆的爸爸从未接受过汤姆
because Tom's dad never accepted Tom,
我想让我儿子明白  我接受他
and I wanted it be known that I accepted my son.
这是有史以来第一次
For the first time ever,
我不介意告诉爸爸我是同性恋
I didn't care about telling my dad that I was gay.
我不介意向他坦白
I didn't care about acknowledging
我和汤姆在一起了
that Tom and I were in a relationship.
我感到无所畏惧
I just felt, like, fearless.
但这一切都没有意义了
But it didn't matter anymore.
汤姆已经走了
And Tom was gone.
我去机场接了玛莎
So, I picked Martha up from the airport,
我们回到了家里
and we went to our house.
她想谈谈银行账户
She wanted to talk about bank accounts --
所有那些我不想提及的事
All these things that I did not want to talk about.
我记得她一直四处打量房间
I remember her looking around the rooms a lot.
我也不愿那样去想
And I didn't really want to think that way.
但我觉得她只想翻看他的东西
I had the feeling that she just wanted to go through his stuff.
她想翻弄谢恩和汤姆的所有衣物
She wanted to go through all of Shane and Tom's clothes.
他让她翻遍了所有抽屉
He let her go through all the drawers.
她甚至想带走谢恩和汤姆共用的电脑
She tried to take the computers that were Shane and Tom's.
就好像谢恩不存在一样
It was just like Shane didn't exist anymore.
谢恩一直很配合她
Shane was more than willing to work with her,
把她想要的汤姆的东西都给了她
give her anything she wanted of Tom's,
但这侵犯了他的隐私
but it started to invade his privacy,
而他对此毫不抱怨
and he wouldn't say anything.
玛莎会就一些东西说三道四
Martha would make a comment about something,
而谢恩则收起了一切感情
and Shane would just stuff the emotions away,
就像小时候孩子们给他起外号时一样
like back when kids would call him names.
我无权说任何话
I couldn't say anything, anyway.
我无权阻止她
I had no legal right to stop her.
汤姆的妈妈和我们一起
So, Tom's mom was waiting, along with us,
等着验尸官移交他的遗体
for the coroner to release his body.
介于这次意外的情况
Due to the circumstances of the accident,
他的遗体必须进行尸检
they had to do an autopsy.
我们开始讨论起葬礼的事
We started talking about the funeral.
她说  不  我们都会被邀请参加
And she said that, no, we're all invited.
我们可以住在他们家
We could stay at their house.
作为家属出席葬礼
You know, "Come as a family.
我们会一起举行葬礼
We'll just do all this together."
她一直在说  "我要带我的宝贝回家"
She was very, you know, "I'm taking my baby home.
"你们都要来  我希望你们出席"
You guys are all coming with. I want you to be there."
然而随着一天天的等待
And then, as the days go on,
她不再谈论葬礼的事
she pretty much quit talking about the funeral
不再提我们出席葬礼
and about us all going
与东部家乡的亲人一起悼念汤姆的事
and sharing Tom with everybody back east.
汤姆的母亲待在另一个房间
Tom's mom was in the other room or even sometimes
甚至有时就坐在我旁边策划葬礼
right next to me making the funeral arrangements
却不让我参与其中
and planning it all out, and I was not a part of it.
好像我是空气  是幽灵
It was like I wasn't there. It was like I was a ghost.
她是一位刚刚失去儿子的母亲
She was a mother who'd just lost her son --
她那20多岁的儿子
her 20-something-year-old son --
除了悲伤  你不能指望她有其他的情绪
So there were no expectations other than grief.
但我没想到她会伤害谢恩
But I didn't think that she was gonna hurt Shane.
我以为她爱谢恩
I thought that she loved Shane.
我觉得肯定有什么不对劲
The feeling I got was something was awry,
但没人会指责她
but nobody could put their finger on it.
然后到了周四早上
And then, that Thursday morning,
玛莎突然说  "我要离开了"
Martha was like, "I got to go."
谢恩说  "我开车送你去机场"
And Shane's like, "I'll drive you to the airport."
她说  "不  我坐出租车"
She's like, "No, I'll get a taxi."
我告诉她  "我不会让你坐出租车的"
I told her, "I'm not gonna let you take a taxi."
我有一种预感
I kind of had a feeling
她知道一些我不知道的事情
that she knew something that I didn't know,
她知道汤姆的遗体随时可以移交
that she knew that his body was gonna be released any moment.
她打包了汤姆的所有衣物
She was packing all Tom's clothes up
好让其陪着他长眠于地下
that she was gonna bury him in,
而她准备给他遗体穿上的夹克
and the jacket that she wanted to put him in
则没有放进行李箱
was not fitting in the suitcase.
谢恩说  "没关系  玛莎"
And Shane's like, "It's okay, Martha.
"我到时候带过去"  但她却说  "不"
I'll just bring it." And she was like, "No.
"绝对不行"
Absolutely not."
现在回过头看
So, maybe looking back now,
那可能就是要发生的事件的征兆
it could have been foreshadowing what could have happened,
她那时候就知道
that she knew then
她不会让谢恩参加葬礼
that she wasn't gonna let Shane come to the funeral.
我把她送到目的地  拥抱了她
And I dropped her off, and we hugged.
请求她有什么情况及时通知我
And I asked her to please keep me updated
以便我知晓那边的情况
so I know what's happening,
她答应我会那样做
and she promised me that she would.
但是我再也没有听到她的消息
But I never heard from her again.
她很感激我们为她儿子做的一切
She was so grateful and so loving towards us
她对我们十分友善
for everything that we did for her son.
她一直哭  拥抱我们  拉着我们的手
She just was crying and hugging us and holding on to us
说什么"我希望成为你们生活的一部分"
and, "I want to be a part of your life.
"我想常来拜访"
I want to come visit."
感觉我们和她建立了感情
It was like we were bonded with her.
到了第二天  她就不见了
And then, the next day, she was gone.
汤姆去世的第二天  我跟他妈妈通过话
I talked to Tom's mom the day after he died.
她说  "一旦葬礼定好时间"
And she said, "I'll let you know
"我会及时通知你"
as soon as I know when the funeral is gonna be
"好让你能够出席"
so that you can be there."
之后就什么动静也没有了
Then, it was pretty much radio silence.
他们没回电告诉我葬礼什么时候举行
They never called me back to tell me when it was,
我很受伤
and I was very hurt.
我看到了报纸上的告示
I see the notice in the newspaper --
他去世后留下了父母诺曼和玛莎  姐姐金和哥哥大卫
可通过殡仪馆向此家庭捐赠
守灵是当天  葬礼是第二天
Wake is this day. Funeral is the next day.
我给汤姆家打电话确认
I called Tom's house to verify,
接电话的亲戚说
and, you know, the relative who answered just said,
"如果报纸上这么说"
"If that's what the paper says,
"那应该没错"
then I would probably go by that."
之后我亲自给
And I personally called back
他家乡不同的太平间打电话
to different mortuaries in his hometown
试图确认这一消息
to try to get information,
可没人愿意告诉我们
and nobody would give us any information.
尽管我们再没听到玛莎的回音
So, although I never heard from Martha,
我妈妈  艾丽克斯和我还是订了机票
my mom and Alex and I, we all booked our plane tickets.
在中途停留时
During our layover,
我接到了汤姆亲戚打来的电话
I received a phone call from one of Tom's relatives.
她告诉我
And she wanted to let me know
汤姆的葬礼不欢迎我
that I wasn't welcome to attend his funeral,
如果我出席
because, if I do show up,
汤姆的叔叔和父亲将对我进行人身攻击
his uncle and his father had planned an attack.
她想让我知道
and she wanted me to know
为了我的人身安全  我不应该出席
that it's for my own safety that I don't go.
我就想  "难道他们要对他开枪吗"
All I could think of -- "Are they gonna shoot him?
"他们要杀了我的儿子吗"
Are they gonna kill my son?"
当我们到了印第安纳州
When we got into Indiana,
汤姆的好友来接我们
one of Tom's best friends picked us up.
艾丽克斯的情绪有些激动
And Alex was hysterical.
离诺克斯市越近  她越抓狂
And the closer we got to Knox, the more hysterical she got.
她一直说"我已经失去了汤姆  我不想再失去你"
And she was saying, "I lost tom. I don't want to lose you, also."
我害怕
I was terrified
他们会对谢恩开枪
that they were gonna come and pull out a gun on Shane.
我记得他[谢恩]说过不止一次
I remember him saying more than once,
"他们很伤心"
"You know, they're in a lot of pain.
"伤心难过的不只是我"
It's not just me that's going through this,"
几乎是在为他们辩解  有点让人受不了
and almost arguing for them, which was maddening.
我是说换了我  我会很生气
I mean, I'd be angry --
会说些"你们不能这样对我"之类的话
"You're not gonna do this to me."
但他没有  他没有如此回应
Nope. He didn't respond that way.
我们找了个秘密地点  商量出了对策
We had a secret location to come up with a plan about,
那就是不去打扰他们
you know, just kind of staying out of their way.
尽管我不能去教堂
And even though I couldn't be in the church,
我还是希望能尽可能的接近汤姆
Like, I still wanted to be as close as I could to Tom.
离他近一点  也算是一种宽慰
You know, just being near was somehow comforting.
当我知道
Once I realized
谢恩被拒绝参加葬礼
that Shane had been banned from attending the funeral,
我便意识到
I realized that's why
他们为何会对具体情况只字不提
they weren't telling anybody when things were.
他们不想让任何消息走漏出去
They basically were keeping all the information close-hold
以阻止谢恩出席
so that Shane couldn't get there.
♪眨眼之间
♪ In the blink of an eye
词曲/演唱: 汤姆
♪瞬息万变
♪ Everything has changed
大概有800人出席
There were probably 800 people there.
其中有一半是为了悼念汤姆
Half of them were there to support Tom,
另一半是为了支持玛莎
And the other half were there to support Martha.
♪如果再给我一天生命
♪ If I could have one more day
♪我会与你一起度过
♪ I'd spend it all with you
棺材在中间
The casket was in the middle.
上面盖着柯尔沃毯子
And it was draped with a Culver blanket
还有一些他在柯尔沃取得的成就
and all of his culver accomplishments,
他妈妈戴着他的柯尔沃戒指
and his mom was wearing his culver ring.
我觉得这些能反映出这个家庭的情况
I think it was very reflective of the family
以及他们如何看待汤姆  那不是我认识的汤姆
and how they viewed Tom, and not the Tom that I knew.
当我起身走到玛莎身边时
When I got up to Martha,
我脑中所想就是
all I could think in my head was,
"为了谢恩  我得亲吻棺材"
"I have to kiss the casket for Shane."
我走到棺材旁边  亲吻了它
And I made my way over to the casket, and I kissed it,
低声说道"谢恩爱你"
and I whispered, you know, "Shane loves you."
葬礼上描述的汤姆
The funeral depicted Tom
基本上剔除了他去加州后的人生
up until the point where he left for California, basically.
发言人都是些汤姆童年时代的人
And the speakers were all from Tom's childhood.
他的钢琴老师
You know, it was his piano teacher
以及柯尔沃的人
and people from Culver.
我从2000级送的花束中拿走了几支花
I took the flowers from the bouquet that the class of 2000 sent,
将其风干  以便我能送给谢恩
and I dried them so I could give those to Shane.
我给他留了份葬礼流程单
And I saved him a program
因为他是汤姆此身的挚爱
because, you know, he is the love of Tom's life.
他值得拥有这些东西
He at least deserves that.
不幸的是  其中并有没提及他
Unfortunately, he wasn't mentioned in it.
做了将近30年的亲人
Families, for literally 30 years,
可以藏匿秘密  直到有人死去
can sweep that secret under the rug until someone dies,
你只得面对现实
and then you have to really face the music.
我认为汤姆的父母就是这样
And I think that's what happened to Tom's parents.
他们有个很棒的孩子
They had this great child.
他聪明  有才华  有很多正能量
He was smart and talented -- lots of positive things.
但有一个积极的方面
But the one positive thing
他们不愿向亲友吹捧的是
that they didn't want to brag to their friends about
汤姆有个出色的伴侣
is that Tom had an amazing partner,
他们因此感到羞耻
'cause they were ashamed.
所以他们所做的是
And so what they did
将其从历史中抹去
is they literally erased it from the history books
该内容现在无法显示
比如关闭他的Facebook账户
by shutting down his facebook page,
拒绝让谢恩出席葬礼
by disinviting Shane to the funeral,
甚至在葬礼上对谢恩只字不提
to not even mentioning him there,
这大概是对一个人的记忆
which is the most insulting thing
最具侮辱性的举动
anyone could ever do to a person's memory.
他们不是反对同性恋婚姻
They're not fighting against gay marriage.
他们不是反对有一个同性恋儿子
They're not fighting against having a gay son.
他们是在反对爱情
What they're fighting against is love,
谁会反对爱情
And who fights against love?
我们回来之后
When we came back,
我们决定自己办悼念会纪念真正的汤姆
we decided to have our own memorial to celebrate who Tom was.
♪今天  你走了
♪Today you're gone
♪今天  你离我而去
♪Today, you left me
谢恩将他[汤姆]家人的照片也放了进去
Shane included pictures of his family
♪前往天堂
♪You left me for heaven
尽管他们没有这样对待他
even though they hadn't reciprocated.
谢恩拿出了
Shane had pictures there
汤姆妈妈爸爸  哥哥姐姐的照片
with Tom's mom and dad and brother and sister.
♪我跪倒在地
♪I'm on my knees
他请来了瓦萨的人  柯尔沃的人
He brought people from Vassar, brought people from Culver,
♪哭泣  乞求
♪Crying and begging
还有他在加州的朋友
and his friends in California.
♪告诉我这只是梦一场
♪Please let me be dreaming
大家都在
Everybody was there.
尽管我们大多数人
Even though a lot of us,
不是很熟悉  或几乎不认识
maybe we weren't super close and barely know each other,
但他是我们共同的挚友
Somehow that same guy was all of our best friend.
♪告诉我这只是个梦
♪Please let me be dreaming
♪年少而美丽的男孩
♪Young, beautiful boy
我写了《美丽的男孩》
I wrote "Beautiful boy"
♪走向了金色大门
♪Making his way up to the Golden doors
那句汤姆走向金色大门的歌词
And the line about Tom making his way up to the golden doors
是给那些信奉基督原教旨主义的人的答案
as an answer to the fundamentalist christians out there
♪时间不会抹去
♪Time will not erase
他们认为同性恋上不了天堂
who may believe that gay people won't go to heaven.
♪我们脸上为你留下的眼泪
♪All of the tears streaming down our faces for you
对他们  我想说"不是吧"
And to that, I would say, "Really?
"汤姆  唱诗班歌手  拿奖拿到手软  标准的美国男孩"
"Tom, the choir-singing, trophy-winning, all-american boy
♪我们会想念你的  亲爱的男孩
♪We'll miss you baby boy
"他在MySpace上把上帝当作自己的英雄"
"who listed god as his hero on his myspace page,
"他会下地狱?"
really in hell?"
我不这么认为
I don't think so.
如果汤姆都上不了天堂  也没什么人能上天堂了
If Tom didn't go to heaven, then nobody's going to heaven.
♪记得
♪Remembering...
如果你相信天使
If you believe in angels,
♪你微笑的样子
♪The way your smile
汤姆很像一个长着人类外表的天使
Tom was as close to that as would ever come in a human form.
♪让我的世界一片光明
♪Made my world alright
他心中毫无阴暗
He had no darkness in him whatsoever.
他是个超级积极向上的人
He was the ueber-positive one.
所以大家都很担心谢恩会如何应对
So, everybody was really nervous about how Shane was gonna be,
在这个糟糕而创伤的经历之后
you know, post this horrible, traumatic loss.
汤姆去世后我陪了谢恩大概一个月
I stayed with Shane after Tom passed away for a month.
我告诉谢恩"只要你需要  我一直陪着你"
I told Shane, "I'll stay here as long as you need me,"
但是登上回家的飞机
But getting on that plane
是我这辈子做的最艰难的事
was the hardest thing I've ever done in my life.
你不想离开他
You know, you don't want to leave him,
因为他这么脆弱
'cause he was fragile.
汤姆
Hey, Tom.
谢恩的视频日记 2011年5月
这是真的吗
Is this happening?
这一切都是真的吗
Is this really happening?
那些人都说
To all those people that, um,
同性恋
say that gay people are
不能相爱
unable to love.
我问每一个丧偶的丈夫和妻子
Can I ask every single husband and wife,
我的这种感受
that is in love
这种感受
to just
我的这种感受就是爱
to just feel what I'm feeling,
哪怕十分钟
Even -- even for 10 minutes. And, um...
但是真的
But, really, I --
我不希望任何人经历这种伤痛
I don't wish this upon anybody. I don't.
2011年7月
我终于给你买了戒指
I finally bought you your ring.
抱歉
I'm sorry that I didn't
我没有早点给你买
I didn't get you one sooner.
我在里面刻上了"嗒嗒嗒"
I put "Tap, tap, tap" inside.
我常常在想一件事
One thing that I'm thinking about is, like, well, you know,
2011年9月
如果我们最初不隐藏这份爱
what would have our relationship been like
我们的关系会怎么样
if we wouldn't have had to have hid it from the beginning,
我会对你更深情
And would I have been able to just
更爱你一点吗
be more affectionate and just give you more love?
如果我们存在  我们相爱
If who we are and how we,
是一种罪恶
you know, loved each other is a sin,
我们要一辈子
in that we have to live,
因此而受罚
you know, eternity suffering because of this.
我觉得上帝不会故意让我们过这种生活
I don't think god would purposely set us up to live a life
让我们不停地和本性斗争
of just constantly fighting the urge to be who we are,
我真的不想相信
and I really don't want to believe that.
生日快乐
Happy birthday to you.
谢恩的视频日记
我大脑里有种想法
You know, there's a part of me that thinks
也许我该向谁倾诉或者表露
maybe I should I tell someone or maybe I should show someone,
我的真实感受
you know, how I'm really feeling
而不是告诉大家我很好
instead of just telling everyone I'm okay.
我一点都不好
And I'm not okay.
生日快乐
Happy birthday to you.
悲伤的是失去你之后
It's sad that it took losing you
2011年11月
我才明白生命中最重要的是什么
to see what's really important in life.
真正重要的是尽全力去爱
All that really counts is just loving as much as we can
而不是害怕被爱
and not, you know, being afraid to be loved.
之前我吃得不多
Before, I was not eating enough,
现在我只想大吃特吃
and then now all I want to do is eat everything --
高脂肪的  冰淇林  煎饼  红葡萄
fat stuff, ice cream, pancakes...red vines.
♪编钟敲响  我望向窗外
♪ Black tower chimes, as I watch through my window
今天我要搭飞机去泰姬陵
Today I'm going on a plane to see the Taj Mahal,
♪雪花飞舞  如蒲公英飘散
♪ Snowflakes have scattered, like dandelion fur
印度  新德里
爱情的伟大纪念  我们旅行列表里的下一项
the great monument to love, which was next on our list.
♪礼物扎着蕾丝绶带
♪ Presents are covered in ribbons and laces
谢恩的视频日记  2011年12月25日
♪远方来信  开心欢快
♪ Long distance tidings, so happy and bright
圣诞节去泰姬陵
Going to the Taj Mahal on Christmas,
圣诞节很棒
Christmas Day is a pretty cool thing, so...
♪点燃烟火  噼噼啪啪
♪ Lighting the fire, that crackles and pops
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas.
♪我们欢聚  在节日夜晚
♪ Togetherness lives, on this holiday night
我只是希望大家都能理解
I just wish that all of us humans understood
我们并没有区别
that we're all the same.
♪每年此刻  互致帮助和欢乐
♪ It's that time of year to give help and good cheer
世界上的所有人  无论什么类型
Everyone in the world, all different types of people,
无论信仰什么宗教
all different religions.
我们只是想快乐
We all just want to be happy.
♪我们欢聚  在节日夜晚
♪ Togetherness lives on this holiday night
♪唱歌跳舞  与我们所爱
♪ Singing and dancing with those who are dear
我们只是想被爱
We all just want to be loved.
谢谢你  汤姆
So, thank you, Tom.
♪神奇一刻  施与及友善
♪ It's a magical time, to be giving and kind
谢谢你爱我
Thank you for loving me.
♪传递和平友爱欢快  在节日夜晚
♪ Spread peace, love and joy, on this holiday night
感谢你把人生中的最后岁月给了我
Thank you for giving me the last years of your life.
我觉得我有责任  或者说是职责
I feel like that's my responsibility, like, my duty now,
像你一样的生活
to live life like you did.
几个月后
A few months later,
我回到了印第安纳
I went back to Indiana.
我觉得我需要再看一次汤姆的坟墓
I felt like I just needed to see Tom's grave one more time.
我仍然不敢相信
I still can't believe
第一个圣诞节之后发生了这么多事
how much has happened since that first Christmas.
我们各自登机  回家
When we were each getting on a plane, heading home,
终于告诉对方我们的真实感受
and we finally told each other how we felt.
谢恩  你让我感觉自己是世界上最幸运的人
我们应该考虑下我们想一起做什么
比方说在大海里游泳
下雨天整天待在家看电影
买一处房子  养一条狗
还有养一个小孩
教他骑车
上学第一天开车送他去学校
我们在桌旁用餐
狗在脚下等着接掉下来的食物
去野餐  躺在星空下的草坪上
好  我们现在要起飞了
我们一起生活会很愉快
希望彼此能一直保有这种感觉
会的  汤姆  我爱你  我已经想你了
我的心属于你  谢恩·彼特尼·克罗恩
我到墓地那里
When I got to the cemetery,
非常惊讶地发现
I was surprised to see that
汤姆的父母给他立了块墓碑
Tom's parents had bought him a monument
也为自己立了墓碑
with a place for themselves, not next to each other,
诺曼·G
1947年10月4日-
汤姆的墓碑在他们中间
but on either side of their son,
玛莎·F
1951年8月18日-
好像仍试图使他远离什么事或者什么人
as though they're still trying to keep him from something or someone.
很难相信即使到现在
It's just -- it's hard to believe that even now
托马斯·李·布莱德格鲁
1982年4月22日-2011年5月7日
他们仍然否认汤姆的本性
Tom is still being denied the promise of his own name.
这种感觉就好像
It really does feel like
他现在代表我们所有人
he's standing in for all of us now,
代表所有
I mean, like, for all gay people
梦想有朝一日能结婚的同性恋者
who dream of getting married some day.
我想我永远无法理解
I guess I'll never understand
为什么本该最爱他的人
why the ones who are supposed to love him the most
却想方设法地反对他做回自己
fight the hardest to keep him from being who he was.
也许汤姆最伟大之处在于
Maybe the greatest thing about Tom
无论如何他都爱着他的父母
is how much he loved them anyway.
我记得我站在那里想
I just remember standing there and thinking
如果我可以和他父母说一句话
that if there's one thing that I could say to his parents,
那就是
here's what it would be --
"这不是你们儿子的纪念碑"
"This is not the monument to your son.
"他是你们的纪念碑"
He was the monument to you."
字幕总监制:   大伟昔
翻译:  灰灰是菇凉    紫玉    嘟嘟矢
翻译:  阿包包  潇湘月影  No. Zero  小白龙
翻译:  妞儿  大卫熊  奶油花  oktobertanz
时间轴:  aaaBao  阿丹  今  No. Zero
校对：大伟昔   特效:  灰灰是菇凉
♪我念三年级时
♪ When I was in the third grade
♪以为自己是基
♪ I thought that I was gay
♪因为我会画画  我叔叔也是基
♪ 'cause I could draw, my uncle was
♪我还把房间整得一尘不染
♪ And I kept my room straight
♪我跟妈说  边说边流泪
♪ I told my mom, tears rushing down my face
♪她却说  本  你幼儿园起就爱妹子
♪ She's like "Ben, you've loved girls since before pre-k"
♪算了  她说得有道理  不是吗
♪ Trippin' Yeah, I guess she had a point, didn't she
♪传统的思绪在我的心头浮现
♪ Bunch of stereotypes all in my head
♪做算术我以为就像
♪ I remember doing the math like
♪嘿  我可擅长棒球联合会
♪ "Yeah, I'm good at little league"
♪这种先入为主
♪ A preconceived idea of what it all meant
♪给喜欢同性的人
♪ For those that liked the same sex
♪都打上另类标签
♪ Had the characteristics
♪右翼保守党认为这是后天人为
♪ The right-wing conservatives think it's a decision
♪可以通过治疗和宗教治愈
♪ And you can be cured with some treatment and religion
♪人们被要求逆天而为
♪ Man-made rewiring of a predisposition
♪简直在扮演上帝
♪ Playing god
♪就这样吧
♪Aw, naw, here we go
♪勇敢的美国人仍畏惧未可知的东西
♪America the brave still fears what we don't know
♪神爱世人  被莫名奇妙地忘记
♪And god loves all his children is somehow forgotten
♪我们却妄加解读3500年前的圣经
♪But we paraphrase a book written 3,500 years ago
♪我不知道
♪I don't know
♪我无法改变
♪And I can't change
♪即使努力
♪Even if I tried
♪即使情愿
♪Even if I wanted to
♪我无法改变
♪And I can't change
♪即使努力
♪Even if I tried
♪即使情愿
♪Even if I wanted to
♪吾爱  吾爱  吾爱
♪My love, my love, my love
♪她予我温暖
♪She keeps me warm
♪我若是基
♪If I was gay
♪会被嘻哈族讨厌吧
♪I would think hip-hop hates me
♪瞧瞧最近油管上的评论
♪Have you read the youtube comments lately
♪大伙都说  "呸  跟基佬似的"
♪"Man, that's gay" Gets dropped on the daily
♪而丝毫不觉得这话有何不妥
♪We become so numb to what we're saying
♪这压抑人性的文化
♪A culture founded from oppression
♪让我们如何去接纳
♪Yet we don't have acceptance for 'em
♪戏谑地在彼此留言板上写"娘炮"
♪Call each other faggots behind the keys of a message board
♪无视这词语根源深处的仇恨
♪A word rooted in hate, yet our genre still ignores it
♪同性爱竟成劣类代名词
♪Gay is synonymous with the lesser
♪正是这仇恨掀起了宗教血腥
♪It's the same hate that's caused wars from religion
♪罔论性别与肤色斗争
♪Gender to skin color
♪一副皮囊而已
♪The complexion of your pigment
♪这斗争引领人们示威静坐
♪The same fight that led people to walk-outs and sit-ins
♪天赋人权
♪It's human rights for everybody
♪众生平等
♪There is no difference
♪坚持住  做自己
♪Live on, and be yourself
♪在教堂里我还学到了其它东西
♪When I was at church, they taught me something else
♪若口吐仇恨这类罪恶的字眼
♪If you preach hate at the service those words aren't anointed
♪就会玷污洗涤你的圣水
♪That holy water that you soak in has been poisoned
♪面对那些人权被践踏的人们
♪When everyone else is more comfortable remaining voiceless
♪多数人选择沉默着回避
♪Rather than fighting for humans that have had their rights stolen
♪我不会
♪I might not be the same
♪这不重要
♪But that's not important
♪不平等则无自由
♪No freedom till we're equal
♪没错  我挺你们
♪Damn right, I support it
♪我不知道
♪I don't know
♪爱即是容忍
♪Love is patient
我们邀请了布莱德格鲁一家参与此纪录片的拍摄
♪爱即是感恩
♪Love is kind
他们没有答复
♪爱即是容忍
♪Love is patient
♪爱即是感恩
♪Love is kind
汤姆逝世周年之际  谢恩上传了一段视频讲述他们的故事
♪我于寂静之声中醒转
♪Well, I woke u p to the sound of silence
观众达数百万人次
♪哭声尖利如薄刃划过掌心
♪The cries were cutting like knives in a fist fight
谢恩  你们的故事在世间流传  如星火燎原
-扎克·M
♪你流连于杯中物
♪And I found you with a bottle of wine
谢恩  这段视频在澳洲已是人尽皆知  汤姆的死并非毫无意义
-马蒂·C
♪布幔遮着脸庞
♪Your head in the curtains
♪心中荡漾着节日的狂欢
♪And heart like the fourth of July
拿出勇气来  谢恩  来自法国的新朋友
-纪尧姆
♪你言词凿凿
♪You swore and said
♪"我们并非那熠熠繁星"
♪"We are not we are not shining stars"
谢恩  永远不要放弃
-来自墨西哥的丹卡洛
♪我怎会不知
♪This I know
♪也从未敢奢望
♪I never said we are
《或许就是你的故事》
持续在全球范围掀起心灵思想风暴
♪从未试过如此撕心裂肺
♪Though I've never been through hell like that
♪窗页开开关关再映不出你蓦然回首
♪I've closed enough windows to know you can never look back
谢恩  我有同样的经历  完全能感受你的痛苦
-大厨劳埃德63
谢恩  我男友自杀了  感谢你为我们挺身而出
-澳洲克莱恩
♪你也许孤单迷惘
♪If you're lost and alone
♪沉沉坠向未知的虚空
♪Or you're sinking like a stone
失去了爱人  且不知他葬身之处  18年来无一日可释怀
-弄潮男孩
♪挺住
♪Carry on
1996年  我失去了伴侣  失去了一切
-55尤里卡
♪往事依依皆化作你脚下步履坚定
♪May your past be the sound of your feet upon the ground
我是个枪不离手的顽固庄稼汉  但今后我再不会反对这种爱情
-安东Z
♪挺住
♪Carry on
我是基督徒  但也被深深感动  同性爱异性爱并无分别
-劳拉埃文斯93
♪挺住  挺住
♪Carry on, carry on
如果爱一个人也犯法  那我们都是不法之徒
-Mt雷勒
他们的事上了报纸
An article came out in the paper,
我们这里的新闻也播了
And then we had it on our news channels,
许多亲戚感到难以接受
And it was hard for several of my family members
为平等而请愿
看到我儿子跟他的同性伴侣
to see my son on there with his gay partner.
我不觉得困扰  但很多人觉得困扰
It didn't bother me, but it bothered a lot of people.
高调同性恋视频大肆传播
我不理它
I ignore it.
我为谢恩的所作所为感到骄傲
'cause I'm proud of what shane's doing,
而且我永远感激汤姆
And because I'll always be grateful for Tom
为我儿子付出的一切
and what he gave to my son.
他说过很多次
Many times he said, you know,
汤姆不在了  我活着也没意义
"My life is not worth living without Tom."
他就像涅槃重生的凤凰一般
He's risen like a phoenix from the ashes.
谢恩曾经害怕出柜
Shane, the guy who was afraid of coming out
不能接受自己
and accepting who he was,
现在他站在人群的最前面
And now he's in front of the parade
身后飘扬着彩虹旗
with rainbow flags behind him.
他积极地传播正能量
He made something positive out of it,
这正是汤姆的座右铭
which is always Tom's motto.
在反对同性恋歧视的斗争中
Shane gave discrimination against gays
谢恩展现了一种生动难忘的姿态
A beautiful, unforgettable face,
是汤姆的姿态
And that face is Tom.
♪头颅已经爆裂
♪My head is on fire
♪腿脚尚能奔跑
♪But my legs are fine
下列6508位赞助者
通过kickstarter.com为本片募集资金
♪毕竟是我的身体
♪After all, they are mine
♪衣服就丢在地上吧
♪Lay your clothes down on the floor
♪关上房门
♪Close the door
♪握紧电话
♪Hold the phones
♪今夜再没有人能够阻止我们
♪Show me how no one's ever gonna stop us tonight
♪我们就是
♪'cause here we are
♪就是那熠熠繁星
♪We are shining stars
♪坚不可摧
♪We are invincible
♪忠于自我
♪We are who we are
♪在天各一方的黑暗日子里
♪On our darkest day when we're miles away
♪太阳仍会升起  照亮回家的路
♪Sun will come, we will find our way home
♪你也许孤单迷惘
♪If you're lost and alone
♪沉沉坠向未知的虚空
♪Or you're sinking like a stone
♪挺住
♪Carry on
♪往事依依皆化作你脚下步履坚定
♪May your past be the sound of your feet upon the ground
♪挺住
♪Carry on
♪今夜再没有人能够阻止我们
♪No one's ever gonna stop us tonight
♪再没有人
♪No one's ever
♪再没有人能够阻止
♪No one's ever gonna stop
♪今夜再没有人能够阻止我们
♪No one's ever gonna stop us tonight
♪流干了眼泪
♪Tears all fall the same
♪历尽了风霜
♪We all feel the rain
♪我们无从改变
♪We can't change
♪浪迹天涯
♪Everywhere we go
♪只为找寻一缕光明
♪We're lookin' for the sun
♪无处终老
♪Nowhere to grow old
♪此生注定在劫难逃
♪We're always on the run
♪世人唾我们万劫不复
♪They say we'll rot in hell
♪但我不相信
♪But I don't think we will
♪不相信他们论断
♪They've branded us enough
♪禁忌之恋
♪Outlaws of love
♪已然伤痕累累
♪Scars make us who we are
♪无以为家  心痛欲裂
♪Hearts and homes are broken, broken
♪那么远  那么远的旅途
♪Far, we could go so far
♪只需一丝丝  一丝丝慰藉
♪With our minds wide open, open
♪流干了眼泪
♪Tears all fall the same
♪历尽了风霜
♪We all feel the rain
♪我们无从改变
♪We can't change
♪浪迹天涯
♪Everywhere we go
♪只为找寻一缕光明
♪We're lookin' for the sun
♪无处终老
♪Nowhere to grow old
♪此生注定在劫难逃
♪We're always on the run
♪世人唾我们万劫不复
♪They say we'll rot in hell
♪但我不相信
♪But I don't think we will
♪不相信他们论断
♪They've branded us enough
♪禁断之恋
♪Outlaws of love
♪不肖之恋
♪放浪之恋
♪Outlaws of love
♪阶囚之恋
♪地狱之恋
♪Outlaws of love